<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-05-01T14:11:55-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">CORAAL Components</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/01/coraal-components.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CORAAL Components" /><published>2024-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/01/coraal-components</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/01/coraal-components.html"><![CDATA[<hr />
<p><a id="ATL" name="ATL"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">CORAAL:ATL (Atlanta, GA 2017)</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">CORAAL:ATL consists of 13 primary speakers across 14 recordings. The speakers for these recordings are part of a modern Atlanta friendship sphere, where many of the speakers were not born and raised in Atlanta, but rather moved to the city from other locations. Speakers range in age from 22 to 40 years old. Located in Georgia, as of 2020, the city of Atlanta had a population of 498,715, with the black population accounting for 46.7% of that population, while the Atlanta Metropolitan area was over 6.1 million. The city is home to the Martin Luther King Jr. National Historic Site, which is to remember and honor African American history throughout the Civil Rights Movement and Civil War. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Farrington, Charlie, Tyler Kendall, Patrick 'Slay' Brooks, Emma Mullen, and Chloe Tacata. 2020. </span></span><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><em>The Corpus of Regional African American Language: ATL (Atlanta, GA 2017)</em>. Version 2020.05. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Currently available in CORAAL.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a name="DCA"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">CORAAL:DCA (Washington DC 1968)</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">CORAAL:DCA consists of 68 speakers across 74 recordings, originally collected as part of Ralph Fasold's (1972) foundational study of African American Language in Washington, D.C. (Fasold 1972). The speakers were recorded between March 1968 and August 1969, with dates of birth ranging from 1891 to 1958. The 68 speakers selected for CORAAL are not the exact same set of speakers analyzed by Fasold (1972). We have selected speakers from Fasold’s interviews to best represent four age groups and three social class groups, although a balanced demographic matrix is not possible given the emphasis of the original project on young speakers. </span></span><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Metadata for DCA include broad information about speakers’ demographic backgrounds, including fine-grained SEC indices from Fasold's original work.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Fasold, Ralph W. 1972. <em>Tense marking in Black English: A linguistic and social analysis. </em>Arlington, VA: Center for Applied Linguistics.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Kendall, Tyler, Ralph Fasold, Charlie Farrington, Jason McLarty, Shelby Arnson, and Brooke Josler. 2018. The Corpus of Regional African American Language: DCA (Washington DC 1968). Version 2018.10.06. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Currently available in CORAAL.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a name="DCB"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">CORAAL:DCB (Washington DC 2016)</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">CORAAL:DCB consists of 48 primary speakers across 63 audio files, collected specifically for CORAAL. The speakers were recorded between July 2015 and December 2017. Speakers were collected through a friend of a friend network to fill a 4 x 3 demographic matrix similar to that for DCA. The socioeconomic groups for DCB are meant to capture broad social strata and are qualitative labels meant to help orient users around the ordering. Theses are not meant to represent theoretically motivated socioeconomic assessments of individuals, and are not intended to be perfectly analogous to Fasold classifications. Metadata for DCB include broad information about speakers’ demographic backgrounds. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">In addition to the conversational speech available here, 45 of the participants read a short reading passage, which is now available as the <strong><a href="supplements#DCB-stella">CORAAL:DCB Stella Passage Supplement</a></strong>.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Kendall, Tyler, Minnie Quartey, Charlie Farrington, Jason McLarty, Shelby Arnson, and Brooke Josler. 2018. <em>The Corpus of Regional African American Language: DCB (Washington DC 2016)</em>. Version 2018.10.06. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Currently available in CORAAL. </span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a id="DTA" name="DTA"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">CORAAL:DTA (Detroit, MI 1966)</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">CORAAL:DTA consists of 40 primary speakers across 40 audio files, originally collected as part of the Detroit Dialect Study (DDS; Shuy et al. 1967, 1968). The DDS was a foundational study of social stratification in American English in which Roger Shuy and colleagues recorded over 700 white and Black Detroit residents to determine linguistic patterns at play across ethnicity, sex, social class, and age, and the outcomes have informed work on education policy regarding vernacular American English dialects. The speakers were recorded primarily in 1966, with dates of birth ranging from 1887 to 1957. The 40 speakers selected for CORAAL are not the exact same set of speakers analyzed by Wolfram (1969). We have selected speakers to best represent three age groups and three social class groups. Metadata for DTA include broad information about speakers' demographic backgrounds from Shuy's original detailed demographic questionnaire. These recordings were digitized by <strong><a href="https://ptlp.com/en/mediapreserve/overview/about-us/" target="_blank">The MediaPreserve</a></strong> with funding from the <strong><a href="https://www.clir.org/recordings-at-risk/" target="_blank">Recordings at Risk Project</a></strong> at the Council on Library and Information Resources in 2019.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Shuy, Roger W., Walt Wolfram, Charlie Farrington, Tyler Kendall, Jaidan McLean, and Chloe Tacata. 2023. </span></span><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;"><em>The Corpus of Regional African American Language: DTA (Detroit, MI 1966)</em>. Version 2023.06. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Shuy, Roger W., Walter A. Wolfram, and William K. Riley. 1967. “Linguistic Correlates of Social Stratification in Detroit Speech.” East Lansing, MI: Michigan State University.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">———. 1968. <i>Field Techniques in an Urban Language Study</i>. Urban Language Series 3. Washington D.C.: Center for Applied Linguistics.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Wolfram, Walter A. 1969. <i>A Sociolinguistic Description of Detroit Negro Speech</i>. Urban Language Series 5. Washington D.C.: Center for Applied Linguistics.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Currently available in CORAAL.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a name="LES"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">CORAAL:LES (Lower East Side, NY 2008)</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">CORAAL:LES consists of 10 primary speakers across 15 audio files, collected in 2008 and 2009 by Kara Becker as part of her dissertation research on the Lower East Side (LES) of Manhattan while at New York University. The LES was the site of William Labov’s (1966) early sociolinguistic research on English in New York City. Demographically, the neighborhood changed dramatically between the 1960s and the time of Becker’s (2009) dissertation research. As of 2010, most residents (~66%) were non-white with a median income of almost half of the median income for the borough of Manhattan (Becker 2014). </span></span><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Speakers were provided by Becker for CORAAL and range in age from 24 to 84 years old. We do not focus on socioeconomic strata, but focus on providing a distribution across gender and age groups. We have attempted to capture and include in the metadata broad information about speakers’ demographic backgrounds, but leave questions of interpretation up to end users. Metadata for LES include information about speakers’ demographic backgrounds, as well as social class score and a generation value which identifies how long their family has lived in the New York City area.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Becker, Kara. 2009. Regional dialect features on the Lower East Side of New York City: Sociophonetics, ethnicity, and idenity. Ph.D. dissertation. New York City: New York University. &lt;<a href="https://pqdtopen.proquest.com/doc/816713188.html?FMT=ABS" target="_blank">Proquest Link</a>&gt;</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Becker, Kara, Charlie Farrington, Tyler Kendall, Chloe Tacata, and Jaidan McLean. 2021. <em>The Corpus of Regional African American Language: LES (Lower East Side, NY 2008)</em>. Version 2021.07. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Currently available in CORAAL.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a name="PRV"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">CORAAL:PRV (Princeville, NC 2004)</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">CORAAL:PRV consists of 16 primary speakers across 32 audio files, collected by Ryan Rowe, Walt Wolfram, and colleagues for the North Carolina Language and Life Project. Princeville, NC is the oldest town incorporated by African Americans in the United States. Many community members can trace their families back to the original founders of the town. The speakers were recorded between August 2003 and June 2004 and are between 19 and 83 years old. As of the 2000 census, African Americans composed 97% of the population (Rowe 2005). Metadata include basic demographic information </span></span><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">such as education, occupation and length of residence in Princeville. Additional recordings may be available through the Sociolinguistic Archive and Analysis Project (<a href="https://slaap.chass.ncsu.edu/" target="_blank">SLAAP</a>).</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Rowe, Ryan. 2005. <em>The development of African American English in the oldest black town in America</em><em>: Plural -s absence in Princeville, NC</em>. MA Thesis. Raleigh: North Carolina State University.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Rowe, Ryan, Walt Wolfram, Tyler Kendall, Charlie Farrington, and Brooke Josler. 2018. <em>The Corpus of Regional African American Language: PRV (Princeville, NC 2004)</em>. Version 2018.10.06. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Currently available in CORAAL, and visit Princeville's <a href="http://www.language-archives.org/item/oai:ncslaap.lib.ncsu.edu:1" target="_blank">OLAC</a> entry for <a href="https://slaap.chass.ncsu.edu/" target="_blank">SLAAP</a>.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a name="ROC"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">CORAAL:ROC (Rochester, NY 2016)</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">CORAAL:ROC consists of 14 primary speakers across 13 audio files, collected in 2016 and 2017 by Sharese King as part of her dissertation research in Rochester, New York.</span></span><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"> Rochester is a city on Lake Ontario, in Monroe County in western New York state. Since the early twentieth century, Rochester has been home to a large African American population (King 2018). Speakers were provided by King for CORAAL from a larger dataset to fill a 2 x 3 demographic matrix and range in age from 24 to 80 years old. We do not focus on socioeconomic strata, but focus on providing a distribution across gender and age groups. We have attempted to capture and include in the metadata broad information about speakers’ demographic backgrounds, but leave questions of interpretation up to end users. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">King, Sharese. 2018. <em>Exploring social and linguistic diversity across African Americans from Rochester, New York</em>. Ph.D. dissertation. Palo Alto, CA: Stanford University. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">King, Sharese, Charlie Farrington, Tyler Kendall, Emma Mullen, Shelby Arnson, and Lucas Jenson. 2020. <em>The Corpus of Regional African American Language</em><em>: ROC (Rochester, NY 2018)</em>. Version 2020.05. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Currently available in CORAAL.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a id="VLD" name="VLD"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">CORAAL:VLD (Valdosta, GA 2017)</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">CORAAL:VLD consists of 12 primary speakers across 14 recordings, collected in 2017 and 2019 by Minnie Quartey for CORAAL. Located in southern Georgia, Valdosta has a population of over 56,000 residents, over 51% of whom are African American. Since the early nineteenth century, Valdosta has been home to a large African American population, particularly since the Civil War where it served as a place of refuge for many fleeing other parts of Georgia where more battles were being fought. Speakers were interviewed by Quartey to fill a 2 x 3 demographic matrix and range in age from 21 to 83 years old. The majority of speakers had a close relationship with the interviewer prior to being interviewed. Metadata includes broad information about speakers’ demographic backgrounds.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Quartey, Minnie, Charlie Farrington, Tyler Kendall, Lucas Jenson, Chloe Tacata, and Jaidan McLean. 2020. <em>The Corpus of Regional African American Language: VLD (Valdosta, GA 2017)</em>. Version 2021.07. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Currently available in CORAAL.</span></span></div>
<p style="text-align: right;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><a href="#top" id="back-top" name="back-top">Back to top of page</a></span></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[CORAAL:ATL (Atlanta, GA 2017) CORAAL:ATL consists of 13 primary speakers across 14 recordings. The speakers for these recordings are part of a modern Atlanta friendship sphere, where many of the speakers were not born and raised in Atlanta, but rather moved to the city from other locations. Speakers range in age from 22 to 40 years old. Located in Georgia, as of 2020, the city of Atlanta had a population of 498,715, with the black population accounting for 46.7% of that population, while the Atlanta Metropolitan area was over 6.1 million. The city is home to the Martin Luther King Jr. National Historic Site, which is to remember and honor African American history throughout the Civil Rights Movement and Civil War. Farrington, Charlie, Tyler Kendall, Patrick 'Slay' Brooks, Emma Mullen, and Chloe Tacata. 2020. The Corpus of Regional African American Language: ATL (Atlanta, GA 2017). Version 2020.05. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. Currently available in CORAAL. CORAAL:DCA (Washington DC 1968) CORAAL:DCA consists of 68 speakers across 74 recordings, originally collected as part of Ralph Fasold's (1972) foundational study of African American Language in Washington, D.C. (Fasold 1972). The speakers were recorded between March 1968 and August 1969, with dates of birth ranging from 1891 to 1958. The 68 speakers selected for CORAAL are not the exact same set of speakers analyzed by Fasold (1972). We have selected speakers from Fasold’s interviews to best represent four age groups and three social class groups, although a balanced demographic matrix is not possible given the emphasis of the original project on young speakers. Metadata for DCA include broad information about speakers’ demographic backgrounds, including fine-grained SEC indices from Fasold's original work. Fasold, Ralph W. 1972. Tense marking in Black English: A linguistic and social analysis. Arlington, VA: Center for Applied Linguistics. Kendall, Tyler, Ralph Fasold, Charlie Farrington, Jason McLarty, Shelby Arnson, and Brooke Josler. 2018. The Corpus of Regional African American Language: DCA (Washington DC 1968). Version 2018.10.06. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. Currently available in CORAAL. CORAAL:DCB (Washington DC 2016) CORAAL:DCB consists of 48 primary speakers across 63 audio files, collected specifically for CORAAL. The speakers were recorded between July 2015 and December 2017. Speakers were collected through a friend of a friend network to fill a 4 x 3 demographic matrix similar to that for DCA. The socioeconomic groups for DCB are meant to capture broad social strata and are qualitative labels meant to help orient users around the ordering. Theses are not meant to represent theoretically motivated socioeconomic assessments of individuals, and are not intended to be perfectly analogous to Fasold classifications. Metadata for DCB include broad information about speakers’ demographic backgrounds. In addition to the conversational speech available here, 45 of the participants read a short reading passage, which is now available as the CORAAL:DCB Stella Passage Supplement. Kendall, Tyler, Minnie Quartey, Charlie Farrington, Jason McLarty, Shelby Arnson, and Brooke Josler. 2018. The Corpus of Regional African American Language: DCB (Washington DC 2016). Version 2018.10.06. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. Currently available in CORAAL. CORAAL:DTA (Detroit, MI 1966) CORAAL:DTA consists of 40 primary speakers across 40 audio files, originally collected as part of the Detroit Dialect Study (DDS; Shuy et al. 1967, 1968). The DDS was a foundational study of social stratification in American English in which Roger Shuy and colleagues recorded over 700 white and Black Detroit residents to determine linguistic patterns at play across ethnicity, sex, social class, and age, and the outcomes have informed work on education policy regarding vernacular American English dialects. The speakers were recorded primarily in 1966, with dates of birth ranging from 1887 to 1957. The 40 speakers selected for CORAAL are not the exact same set of speakers analyzed by Wolfram (1969). We have selected speakers to best represent three age groups and three social class groups. Metadata for DTA include broad information about speakers' demographic backgrounds from Shuy's original detailed demographic questionnaire. These recordings were digitized by The MediaPreserve with funding from the Recordings at Risk Project at the Council on Library and Information Resources in 2019. Shuy, Roger W., Walt Wolfram, Charlie Farrington, Tyler Kendall, Jaidan McLean, and Chloe Tacata. 2023. The Corpus of Regional African American Language: DTA (Detroit, MI 1966). Version 2023.06. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. Shuy, Roger W., Walter A. Wolfram, and William K. Riley. 1967. “Linguistic Correlates of Social Stratification in Detroit Speech.” East Lansing, MI: Michigan State University. ———. 1968. Field Techniques in an Urban Language Study. Urban Language Series 3. Washington D.C.: Center for Applied Linguistics. Wolfram, Walter A. 1969. A Sociolinguistic Description of Detroit Negro Speech. Urban Language Series 5. Washington D.C.: Center for Applied Linguistics. Currently available in CORAAL. CORAAL:LES (Lower East Side, NY 2008) CORAAL:LES consists of 10 primary speakers across 15 audio files, collected in 2008 and 2009 by Kara Becker as part of her dissertation research on the Lower East Side (LES) of Manhattan while at New York University. The LES was the site of William Labov’s (1966) early sociolinguistic research on English in New York City. Demographically, the neighborhood changed dramatically between the 1960s and the time of Becker’s (2009) dissertation research. As of 2010, most residents (~66%) were non-white with a median income of almost half of the median income for the borough of Manhattan (Becker 2014). Speakers were provided by Becker for CORAAL and range in age from 24 to 84 years old. We do not focus on socioeconomic strata, but focus on providing a distribution across gender and age groups. We have attempted to capture and include in the metadata broad information about speakers’ demographic backgrounds, but leave questions of interpretation up to end users. Metadata for LES include information about speakers’ demographic backgrounds, as well as social class score and a generation value which identifies how long their family has lived in the New York City area. Becker, Kara. 2009. Regional dialect features on the Lower East Side of New York City: Sociophonetics, ethnicity, and idenity. Ph.D. dissertation. New York City: New York University. &lt;Proquest Link&gt; Becker, Kara, Charlie Farrington, Tyler Kendall, Chloe Tacata, and Jaidan McLean. 2021. The Corpus of Regional African American Language: LES (Lower East Side, NY 2008). Version 2021.07. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. Currently available in CORAAL. CORAAL:PRV (Princeville, NC 2004) CORAAL:PRV consists of 16 primary speakers across 32 audio files, collected by Ryan Rowe, Walt Wolfram, and colleagues for the North Carolina Language and Life Project. Princeville, NC is the oldest town incorporated by African Americans in the United States. Many community members can trace their families back to the original founders of the town. The speakers were recorded between August 2003 and June 2004 and are between 19 and 83 years old. As of the 2000 census, African Americans composed 97% of the population (Rowe 2005). Metadata include basic demographic information such as education, occupation and length of residence in Princeville. Additional recordings may be available through the Sociolinguistic Archive and Analysis Project (SLAAP). Rowe, Ryan. 2005. The development of African American English in the oldest black town in America: Plural -s absence in Princeville, NC. MA Thesis. Raleigh: North Carolina State University. Rowe, Ryan, Walt Wolfram, Tyler Kendall, Charlie Farrington, and Brooke Josler. 2018. The Corpus of Regional African American Language: PRV (Princeville, NC 2004). Version 2018.10.06. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. Currently available in CORAAL, and visit Princeville's OLAC entry for SLAAP. CORAAL:ROC (Rochester, NY 2016) CORAAL:ROC consists of 14 primary speakers across 13 audio files, collected in 2016 and 2017 by Sharese King as part of her dissertation research in Rochester, New York. Rochester is a city on Lake Ontario, in Monroe County in western New York state. Since the early twentieth century, Rochester has been home to a large African American population (King 2018). Speakers were provided by King for CORAAL from a larger dataset to fill a 2 x 3 demographic matrix and range in age from 24 to 80 years old. We do not focus on socioeconomic strata, but focus on providing a distribution across gender and age groups. We have attempted to capture and include in the metadata broad information about speakers’ demographic backgrounds, but leave questions of interpretation up to end users. King, Sharese. 2018. Exploring social and linguistic diversity across African Americans from Rochester, New York. Ph.D. dissertation. Palo Alto, CA: Stanford University. King, Sharese, Charlie Farrington, Tyler Kendall, Emma Mullen, Shelby Arnson, and Lucas Jenson. 2020. The Corpus of Regional African American Language: ROC (Rochester, NY 2018). Version 2020.05. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. Currently available in CORAAL. CORAAL:VLD (Valdosta, GA 2017) CORAAL:VLD consists of 12 primary speakers across 14 recordings, collected in 2017 and 2019 by Minnie Quartey for CORAAL. Located in southern Georgia, Valdosta has a population of over 56,000 residents, over 51% of whom are African American. Since the early nineteenth century, Valdosta has been home to a large African American population, particularly since the Civil War where it served as a place of refuge for many fleeing other parts of Georgia where more battles were being fought. Speakers were interviewed by Quartey to fill a 2 x 3 demographic matrix and range in age from 21 to 83 years old. The majority of speakers had a close relationship with the interviewer prior to being interviewed. Metadata includes broad information about speakers’ demographic backgrounds. Quartey, Minnie, Charlie Farrington, Tyler Kendall, Lucas Jenson, Chloe Tacata, and Jaidan McLean. 2020. The Corpus of Regional African American Language: VLD (Valdosta, GA 2017). Version 2021.07. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. Currently available in CORAAL. Back to top of page]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/24/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2024-04-24T13:57:30-04:00</published><updated>2024-04-24T13:57:30-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/24/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2024/04/24/welcome-to-jekyll.html"><![CDATA[<p>You’ll find this post in your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_posts</code> directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll serve</code>, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</p>

<p>Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:</p>

<p><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP</code></p>

<p>Where <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">YEAR</code> is a four-digit number, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MONTH</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">DAY</code> are both two-digit numbers, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">MARKUP</code> is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.</p>

<p>Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-ruby" data-lang="ruby"><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="nb">puts</span> <span class="s2">"Hi, </span><span class="si">#{</span><span class="nb">name</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>
<span class="k">end</span>
<span class="n">print_hi</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'Tom'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="c1">#=&gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home">Jekyll docs</a> for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at <a href="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll’s GitHub repo</a>. If you have questions, you can ask them on <a href="https://talk.jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll Talk</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Harlem 1969 (Walt Wolfram Recordings)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/06/25/harlem-1969-walt-wolfram-recordings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Harlem 1969 (Walt Wolfram Recordings)" /><published>2023-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/06/25/harlem-1969-walt-wolfram-recordings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/06/25/harlem-1969-walt-wolfram-recordings.html"><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">The <em>Harlem 1969</em> recordings were made by a research team led by Walt Wolfram. The research questions focused on expanding the descriptive accounts of a range of social dialects in the US. From a theoretical point of view, this research study analyzed the relationship between language contact, bilingualism, and sociolinguistic variables that had been well-studied in other northern Black communities. And, like his prior collaborative work in Detroit and Washington DC, Wolfram et al. (1971:2) ultimately had an applied viewpoint: "We need to know how the various social dialects in the United States are structured if we are going to base our educational strategies on sound descriptive facts."</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">The sociolinguistic interviews were conducted in August 1969 at a summer camp in Lake Champion, New York. Participants were interviewed by either Walt Wolfram, Ralph Fasold, or Roger W. Shuy.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">This sample, called <em>Harlem Sounds</em>, focuses on the particular line of questions about ritualistic language in the community, particularly <em>sounding</em>, which "involves insulting someone's mother, although other relatives might also be mentioned (e.g., grandmother, father, uncle). The presuppositions under which the activity is conducted are shared by the participants, namely, that the insult is not literally true. The proper cultural response to a ritualistic insult is another ritualistic insult" Wolfram (1974:258).</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;"><em>Harlem Sounds</em> comes from <strong><a href="https://www.lib.ncsu.edu/findingaids/mc00354" target="_blank">The Walt Wolfram Papers 1971-1998</a></strong> special collection at North Carolina State University. The original tape was digitized by Brooke Wallig at North Carolina State University in January 2016. The tape reel, a Scotch magnetic tape 150 extra length</span></span>, <span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">was not separated into tracks, and contained 20 excerpts, totalling 45.3 minutes (~7700 words).</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Charlie Farrington transcribed and prepared the excerpts for upload.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><strong><em><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Download here: </span></span></em><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><a href="http://lingtools.uoregon.edu/coraal/supplements/HLM1969.tar.gz">http://lingtools.uoregon.edu/coraal/supplements/HLM1969.tar.gz </a></span></span></strong></div>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Table 1. Demographic information by file name, including age, ethnicity, borough, region within Borough (see figure 1). <em>Race of peer contacts</em> was taken directly from interview report forms.</span></span></p>
<table class="table table--responsive table--borders"><tbody class="table__body"><tr class="table__row__header"><th class="table__cell table__header" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:16px;">File name</span></span></th><th class="table__cell table__header" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:16px;">Age</span></span></th><th class="table__cell table__header" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Ethnicty</span></th><th class="table__cell table__header" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;">NYC Borough</span></th><th class="table__cell table__header" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Region</span></th><th class="table__cell table__header" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Interviewer</span></th><th class="table__cell table__header" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Race of Peer Contacts</span></th></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm001&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm001</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">16</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;African American&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Central Harlem&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">West Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;WW&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">WW</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;75% Black&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">75% Black</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm003&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm003</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">15</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;African American&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;110th to 101st, 2nd to 5th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">110th to 101st, 2nd to 5th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;WW&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">WW</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Predominantly Black&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Predominantly Black</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm004&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm004</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">15</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;African American&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;110th to 101st, 2nd to 5th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">110th to 101st, 2nd to 5th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;RF&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">RF</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Black&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm005&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm005</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">17</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Puerto Rican&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Puerto Rican</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;110th to 116th, 2nd to 5th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">110th to 116th, 2nd to 5th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;WW&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">WW</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Half Puerto Rican, half Black&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="border-right: 1px solid transparent; overflow: visible; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><div style="white-space:nowrap;overflow:hidden;position:relative;width:242px;left:3px;"><div style="float:left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Half Puerto Rican, half Black</span></span></div></div></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm006&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm006<sup>a</sup></span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">14</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;African American&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;110th to 101st, 2nd to 5th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">110th to 101st, 2nd to 5th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;WW&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">WW</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Black&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm007&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm007</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">15</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Puerto Rican&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Puerto Rican</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Bronx&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Bronx</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Crotona Park&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Crotona Park</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;RF&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">RF</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Mostly Spanish&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Mostly Spanish</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm008&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm008</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">19</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;African American&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;WW&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">WW</span></span></td><td data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;">&nbsp;</td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm009&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm009</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">16</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Puerto Rican&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Puerto Rican</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;WW&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">WW</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Puerto Rican&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Puerto Rican</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm010&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm010</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">15</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Puerto Rican&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Puerto Rican</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;WW&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">WW</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Half PR, half Black&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Half PR, half Black</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm011&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm011</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">17</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Puerto Rican&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Puerto Rican</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Bronx&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Bronx</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;South of 159th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">South of 159th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;WW&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">WW</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Mostly PR, but some Black&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="border-right: 1px solid transparent; overflow: visible; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><div style="white-space:nowrap;overflow:hidden;position:relative;width:242px;left:3px;"><div style="float:left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Mostly PR, but some Black</span></span></div></div></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm012&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm012</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">14</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;African American&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;110th to 101st, 2nd to 5th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">110th to 101st, 2nd to 5th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;WW&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">WW</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Black&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm013&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm013</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">15</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;African American&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;110th to 101st, 2nd to 5th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">110th to 101st, 2nd to 5th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;RF&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">RF</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Black&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm014&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm014</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">16</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Puerto Rican&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Puerto Rican</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;110th to 116th, 2nd to 5th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">110th to 116th, 2nd to 5th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;RF&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">RF</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Black, PR, Italian&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black, PR, Italian</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm015&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm015</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">16</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;African American&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;110th to 101st, 2nd to 5th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">110th to 101st, 2nd to 5th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;RF&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">RF</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Black&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm016&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm016</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">13</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;African American&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;RF&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">RF</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Black&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm018&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm018</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">17</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Puerto Rican&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Puerto Rican</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;RF&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">RF</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Black&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm020&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm020</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">14</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Puerto Rican&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Puerto Rican</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;110th to 116th, 2nd to 5th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">110th to 116th, 2nd to 5th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;WW&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">WW</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Practically all PR&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Practically all PR</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm021&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm021</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">14</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Puerto Rican&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Puerto Rican</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Bronx&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Bronx</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;South of 159th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">South of 159th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;RWS&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">RWS</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Black and PR&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black and PR</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm022&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm022</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">14</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Puerto Rican&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Puerto Rican</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Harlem&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Harlem</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;110th to 116th, 2nd to 5th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">110th to 116th, 2nd to 5th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;WW&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">WW</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Predominantly PR&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Predominantly PR</span></span></td></tr><tr><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;hlm023&quot;}" data-th="File name" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">hlm023</span></span></td><td class="table__cell" data-th="Age" style="text-align: left; vertical-align: middle;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">17</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Puerto Rican&quot;}" data-th="Ethnicty" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Puerto Rican</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Bronx&quot;}" data-th="NYC Borough" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Bronx</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;South of 159th&quot;}" data-th="Region" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">South of 159th</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;WW&quot;}" data-th="Interviewer" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">WW</span></span></td><td data-sheets-value="{&quot;1&quot;:2,&quot;2&quot;:&quot;Very mixed&quot;}" data-th="Race of Peer Contacts" style="overflow: hidden; padding: 2px 3px; vertical-align: middle; text-align: left;"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Very mixed</span></span></td></tr></tbody></table>
<p><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><sup>a</sup> From North Carolina, only one year in NYC</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Figure 1. Geographical location of informants (from Wolfram 1974:14)</span></span></p>
<p>[[{"fid":"205","view_mode":"default","fields":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":"Map of Harlem and the Bronx, highlighting seven geographic locations where informants are from","field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":"Geographical location of informants from Wolfram 1974"},"link_text":null,"type":"media","field_deltas":{"1":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":"Map of Harlem and the Bronx, highlighting seven geographic locations where informants are from","field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":"Geographical location of informants from Wolfram 1974"}},"attributes":{"alt":"Map of Harlem and the Bronx, highlighting seven geographic locations where informants are from","title":"Geographical location of informants from Wolfram 1974","height":877,"width":688,"class":"media-element file-default","data-delta":"1"}}]]</p>
<p><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:24px;">Citation</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">If you use these recordings, we ask that you cite the following:</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Kendall, Tyler and Charlie Farrington. 2023. The Corpus of Regional African American Language. Version 2023.06. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. [</span></span><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><a href="https://doi.org/10.7264/1ad5-6t35">https://doi.org/10.7264/1ad5-6t35</a>].</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Wolfram, Walt. 1974. Sociolinguistic Aspects of Assimilation. Arlington, VA: Center for Applied Linguistics. &lt;<a href="https://eric.ed.gov/?id=ED091933" target="_blank">https://eric.ed.gov/?id=ED091933</a>&gt;.</span></span></p>
<hr />
<p style="text-align: right;"><a class="cta-button cta-button--standard text--uppercase" href=".">Back to CORAAL Supplements</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Harlem 1969 recordings were made by a research team led by Walt Wolfram. The research questions focused on expanding the descriptive accounts of a range of social dialects in the US. From a theoretical point of view, this research study analyzed the relationship between language contact, bilingualism, and sociolinguistic variables that had been well-studied in other northern Black communities. And, like his prior collaborative work in Detroit and Washington DC, Wolfram et al. (1971:2) ultimately had an applied viewpoint: "We need to know how the various social dialects in the United States are structured if we are going to base our educational strategies on sound descriptive facts." The sociolinguistic interviews were conducted in August 1969 at a summer camp in Lake Champion, New York. Participants were interviewed by either Walt Wolfram, Ralph Fasold, or Roger W. Shuy. This sample, called Harlem Sounds, focuses on the particular line of questions about ritualistic language in the community, particularly sounding, which "involves insulting someone's mother, although other relatives might also be mentioned (e.g., grandmother, father, uncle). The presuppositions under which the activity is conducted are shared by the participants, namely, that the insult is not literally true. The proper cultural response to a ritualistic insult is another ritualistic insult" Wolfram (1974:258). Harlem Sounds comes from The Walt Wolfram Papers 1971-1998 special collection at North Carolina State University. The original tape was digitized by Brooke Wallig at North Carolina State University in January 2016. The tape reel, a Scotch magnetic tape 150 extra length, was not separated into tracks, and contained 20 excerpts, totalling 45.3 minutes (~7700 words). Charlie Farrington transcribed and prepared the excerpts for upload. Download here: http://lingtools.uoregon.edu/coraal/supplements/HLM1969.tar.gz Table 1. Demographic information by file name, including age, ethnicity, borough, region within Borough (see figure 1). Race of peer contacts was taken directly from interview report forms. File nameAgeEthnictyNYC BoroughRegionInterviewerRace of Peer Contactshlm00116BlackHarlemWest HarlemWW75% Blackhlm00315BlackHarlem110th to 101st, 2nd to 5thWWPredominantly Blackhlm00415BlackHarlem110th to 101st, 2nd to 5thRFBlackhlm00517Puerto RicanHarlem110th to 116th, 2nd to 5thWWHalf Puerto Rican, half Blackhlm006a14BlackHarlem110th to 101st, 2nd to 5thWWBlackhlm00715Puerto RicanBronxCrotona ParkRFMostly Spanishhlm00819BlackHarlem125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.WW&nbsp;hlm00916Puerto RicanHarlem125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.WWPuerto Ricanhlm01015Puerto RicanHarlem125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.WWHalf PR, half Blackhlm01117Puerto RicanBronxSouth of 159thWWMostly PR, but some Blackhlm01214BlackHarlem110th to 101st, 2nd to 5thWWBlackhlm01315BlackHarlem110th to 101st, 2nd to 5thRFBlackhlm01416Puerto RicanHarlem110th to 116th, 2nd to 5thRFBlack, PR, Italianhlm01516BlackHarlem110th to 101st, 2nd to 5thRFBlackhlm01613BlackHarlem125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.RFBlackhlm01817Puerto RicanHarlem125th to 113th, east of Lenox Ave.RFBlackhlm02014Puerto RicanHarlem110th to 116th, 2nd to 5thWWPractically all PRhlm02114Puerto RicanBronxSouth of 159thRWSBlack and PRhlm02214Puerto RicanHarlem110th to 116th, 2nd to 5thWWPredominantly PRhlm02317Puerto RicanBronxSouth of 159thWWVery mixed a From North Carolina, only one year in NYC Figure 1. Geographical location of informants (from Wolfram 1974:14) [[{"fid":"205","view_mode":"default","fields":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":"Map of Harlem and the Bronx, highlighting seven geographic locations where informants are from","field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":"Geographical location of informants from Wolfram 1974"},"link_text":null,"type":"media","field_deltas":{"1":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":"Map of Harlem and the Bronx, highlighting seven geographic locations where informants are from","field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":"Geographical location of informants from Wolfram 1974"}},"attributes":{"alt":"Map of Harlem and the Bronx, highlighting seven geographic locations where informants are from","title":"Geographical location of informants from Wolfram 1974","height":877,"width":688,"class":"media-element file-default","data-delta":"1"}}]] Citation If you use these recordings, we ask that you cite the following: Kendall, Tyler and Charlie Farrington. 2023. The Corpus of Regional African American Language. Version 2023.06. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. [https://doi.org/10.7264/1ad5-6t35]. Wolfram, Walt. 1974. Sociolinguistic Aspects of Assimilation. Arlington, VA: Center for Applied Linguistics. &lt;https://eric.ed.gov/?id=ED091933&gt;. Back to CORAAL Supplements]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CORAAL:DCB Stella Passage (Washington DC 2016)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/03/15/coraaldcb-stella-passage-washington-dc-2016.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CORAAL:DCB Stella Passage (Washington DC 2016)" /><published>2023-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/03/15/coraaldcb-stella-passage-washington-dc-2016</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/03/15/coraaldcb-stella-passage-washington-dc-2016.html"><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">As part of the recording process in the CORAAL:DCB (Washington DC 2016) component, most participants read the "Please Call Stella" reading passage from the <strong><a href="http://accent.gmu.edu/index.php" target="_blank">Speech Accent Archive</a></strong> (Steven H. Weinberger at George Mason University):</span></span></p>
<blockquote><p><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Please call Stella. Ask her to bring these things with her from the store: Six spoons of fresh snow peas, five thick slabs of blue cheese, and maybe a snack for her brother Bob. We also need a small plastic snake and a big toy frog for the kids. She can scoop these things into three red bags, and we will go meet her Wednesday at the train station. </span></span></p></blockquote>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">The Supplement contains 21 minutes of total speech. The passage is short, on average 28 seconds in length per speaker,&nbsp;but contains a range of English sounds and sound sequences in a controlled task and&nbsp;can be useful in evaluating stylistic differences in comparison to the conversational speech contained in <strong><a href="components#DCB">CORAAL:DCB</a></strong>, which is from the same speakers.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">The Stella passages were transcribed in Praat by Chloe Tacata and Charlie Farrington. Orthographic transcripts are available as Praat TextGrids (.TextGrid), ELAN files (.eaf), and plain, tab-delimited text (.txt). In addition, the DCB Stella Passage also includes phone-level aligned Praat TextGrids (via the <strong><a href="https://montreal-forced-aligner.readthedocs.io/" target="_blank">Montreal Forced Aligner</a></strong>; McAuliffe et al. 2017). We also include the <strong><a href="https://github.com/JoFrhwld/FAVE" target="_blank">FAVE-Extract</a></strong> (Rosenfelder et al. 2022) vowel measurements.</span> <span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">All files were prepared for upload by Charlie Farrington.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Metadata for the speakers of the DCB Stella Passage are available on the CORAAL Download Site (<strong><a href="http://lingtools.uoregon.edu/coraal/" target="_blank">http://lingtools.uoregon.edu/coraal/</a></strong>).</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><strong><em><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Download here:<br />Audio (.WAV files): </span></span></em><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;"><a href="http://lingtools.uoregon.edu/coraal/supplements/DCB-stella_audio.tar.gz">http://lingtools.uoregon.edu/coraal/supplements/DCB-stella_audio.tar.gz</a> (112 mb)<br /><em>Annotations: </em><a href="http://lingtools.uoregon.edu/coraal/supplements/DCB-stella_annotations.tar.gz">http://lingtools.uoregon.edu/coraal/supplements/DCB-stella_annotations.tar.gz</a> (4 mb)</span></span></strong></div>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">The DCB Stella Passage is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike (4.0) International license (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/). It is available for free and is downloadable from the above link. It is also available as part of CORAAL's Commercial Licenses.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:24px;">Citation</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">If you use these recordings, we ask that you cite the following:</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Farrington, Charlie, Minnie Quartey, Chloe Tacata, and Tyler Kendall. 2023. CORAAL:DCB Stella Passage (Washington DC 2016). Version 2023.03. A Supplement to the Corpus of Regional African American Language. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. [<a href="https://oraal.uoregon.edu/coraal/supplements/dcb-stella">https://oraal.uoregon.edu/coraal/supplements/dcb-stella</a>].</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Kendall, Tyler and Charlie Farrington. 2020. The Corpus of Regional African American Language. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. [</span></span><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><a href="https://doi.org/10.7264/1ad5-6t35">https://doi.org/10.7264/1ad5-6t35</a>].</span></span></p>
<hr />
<p style="text-align: right;"><a class="cta-button cta-button--standard text--uppercase" href=".">Back to CORAAL Supplements</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As part of the recording process in the CORAAL:DCB (Washington DC 2016) component, most participants read the "Please Call Stella" reading passage from the Speech Accent Archive (Steven H. Weinberger at George Mason University): Please call Stella. Ask her to bring these things with her from the store: Six spoons of fresh snow peas, five thick slabs of blue cheese, and maybe a snack for her brother Bob. We also need a small plastic snake and a big toy frog for the kids. She can scoop these things into three red bags, and we will go meet her Wednesday at the train station. The Supplement contains 21 minutes of total speech. The passage is short, on average 28 seconds in length per speaker,&nbsp;but contains a range of English sounds and sound sequences in a controlled task and&nbsp;can be useful in evaluating stylistic differences in comparison to the conversational speech contained in CORAAL:DCB, which is from the same speakers. The Stella passages were transcribed in Praat by Chloe Tacata and Charlie Farrington. Orthographic transcripts are available as Praat TextGrids (.TextGrid), ELAN files (.eaf), and plain, tab-delimited text (.txt). In addition, the DCB Stella Passage also includes phone-level aligned Praat TextGrids (via the Montreal Forced Aligner; McAuliffe et al. 2017). We also include the FAVE-Extract (Rosenfelder et al. 2022) vowel measurements. All files were prepared for upload by Charlie Farrington. Metadata for the speakers of the DCB Stella Passage are available on the CORAAL Download Site (http://lingtools.uoregon.edu/coraal/). Download here:Audio (.WAV files): http://lingtools.uoregon.edu/coraal/supplements/DCB-stella_audio.tar.gz (112 mb)Annotations: http://lingtools.uoregon.edu/coraal/supplements/DCB-stella_annotations.tar.gz (4 mb) The DCB Stella Passage is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike (4.0) International license (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/). It is available for free and is downloadable from the above link. It is also available as part of CORAAL's Commercial Licenses. Citation If you use these recordings, we ask that you cite the following: Farrington, Charlie, Minnie Quartey, Chloe Tacata, and Tyler Kendall. 2023. CORAAL:DCB Stella Passage (Washington DC 2016). Version 2023.03. A Supplement to the Corpus of Regional African American Language. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. [https://oraal.uoregon.edu/coraal/supplements/dcb-stella]. Kendall, Tyler and Charlie Farrington. 2020. The Corpus of Regional African American Language. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. [https://doi.org/10.7264/1ad5-6t35]. Back to CORAAL Supplements]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sociophonetic Variation in AAL</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/sociophonetic-variation-in-aal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sociophonetic Variation in AAL" /><published>2020-11-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-11-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/sociophonetic-variation-in-aal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/17/sociophonetic-variation-in-aal.html"><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size:24px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;">This is a companion webpage to the <em>Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Cognitive Science </em>article "Sources of variation in the speech of African Americans: Perspectives from sociophonetics," by <a href="https://charliefarrington.com/" target="_blank">Charlie Farrington</a>, <a href="https://www.drshareseking.com/" target="_blank">Sharese King</a>, and <a href="https://maryekohn.com/" target="_blank">Mary Kohn</a>.</span></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is a companion webpage to the Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Cognitive Science article "Sources of variation in the speech of African Americans: Perspectives from sociophonetics," by Charlie Farrington, Sharese King, and Mary Kohn. &nbsp;]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Frequently Asked Questions about AAL</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/07/frequently-asked-questions-about-aal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Frequently Asked Questions about AAL" /><published>2020-07-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/07/frequently-asked-questions-about-aal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/07/frequently-asked-questions-about-aal.html"><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size:22px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><strong>What is African American Language?</strong></span></span></p>
<ul><li><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">African American Language (AAL) varieties are spoken by many African American speakers in the United States.&nbsp;Over the past half century, AAL has been the subject of a great deal of research by linguists and other scholars. Click on any of the links below to learn more about AAL, who speaks it, how it developed, and more!</span></span></li><li><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Over several decades, hundreds of researchers have investigated different aspects of AAL. Some prominent early sociolinguists, including William Labov and Walt Wolfram, pioneered the study of the variety. On our <strong><a href="/AAL/Linguists">Find An Expert</a></strong> page, we celebrate the ongoing contributions of Black scholars researching AAL.</span></span></li></ul>
<p><span style="font-size:22px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><strong>Why do you call it "African American Language"?</strong></span></span></p>
<ul><li><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><em>African American Language</em> is a term used to describe language use within the African American community. The speech of African Americans has been called many things by linguists over the years, including Black English, AAVE, AAE, and Ebonics, though these terms may not specifically refer to the same group. Lanehart and Malik (2015:4) suggest that "when speakers know AAL, they know a system of sounds, word and sentence structure, meaning and structural organization of vocabulary items, and other linguistic and metalinguistic information about their language, such as pragmatic rules and the social function of AAL." </span></span></li><li><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">African American speech is better viewed as a continuum rather than one speech variety. Not every speaker uses all features associated with AAL. For other definitions of AAL, check out <strong><a href="/AAL/What-is-AAL">What is AAL and who speaks it</a></strong>?</span></span></li></ul>
<p><span style="font-size:22px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><strong>Why do scholars and teachers care about AAL?</strong></span></span></p>
<ul><li><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Throughout the half century of sociolinguistic work on AAL varieties, several goals for research have occurred at the same time. For example, William Labov's work in New York City, Walt Wolfram's work in Detroit, and Ralph Fasold's work in Washington DC address core theoretical question to the sociolinguistic enterprise, at the same time, this research was federally funded by the US Office of Education with specific interests in the relationship between vernacular AAL and school performance. Research into reading and AAL, teaching strategies, and acquisition followed. As April Baker-Bell (2020:3) recently wrote in her book, <em>Linguistic Justice: Black Language, Literacy, Identity, and Pedagogy</em>, social justice is linguistic justice: </span></span><ul><li><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">"<em>Linguistic justice is a call to action: a call to radically imagine and create a world free of anti-blackness. A call to create an education system where Black students, their language, their literacies, their culture, their creativity, their joy, their imagination, their brilliance, their freedom, their existence, their resistance MATTERS.</em>"</span></span></li></ul></li></ul>
<p><span style="font-size:22px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><strong>What do researchers study about AAL?</strong></span></span></p>
<ul><li><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Researchers study many different aspects of AAL, including linguistic features and how it has changed over time, perceptions and attitudes, the role of AAL in education, language acquisition, regional variation, and bi-dialectalism. For more information, see <strong><a href="/AAL/Linguistic-Patterns">AAL Linguistic Patterns</a></strong>. To learn about some of the researchers who study different aspects of AAL, please see our <strong><a href="/AAL/Linguists">Find an Expert</a></strong> page.</span></span></li></ul>
<p><span style="font-size:22px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><strong>Where did AAL come from?</strong></span></span></p>
<ul><li><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">The origins of AAL have been long debated by linguistic researchers. Several competing positions have emerged, including the Creole Hypothesis, the English Origins Hypothesis, and, most recently, the Substrate Hypothesis. Linguists have used letters written by 18th and 19th century African Americans, written interviews, audio recordings of formerly enslaved individuals, and modern recordings from isolated Black communities to investigate how the speech developed out of the first African Americans and enslaved African peoples in the United States. Most linguists agree that what we now know as AAL primarily developed during the 20th century due to the population movements during the Great Migration and subsequent segregation in large urban centers. For more on the development of AAL, see <strong><a href="/AAL/Development">How did AAL develop?</a></strong></span></span></li></ul>
<p><span style="font-size:22px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><strong>Who speaks AAL?</strong> </span></span></p>
<ul><li><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">It is difficult to estimate the total number of speakers of a variety, since, as mentioned above, AAL is a continuum. It is true that not all African Americans speak an AAL variety and not all speakers of AAL are African Americans. Some African Americans may speak a variety that aligns more with White Mainstream English, and some non-African Americans may incorporate AAL linguistic features into their speech.</span></span></li></ul>
<p><span style="font-size:22px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><strong>Is AAL a language or a dialect?</strong></span></span></p>
<ul><li><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">For linguists, the distinction between languages and dialects is often unclear and can be due to sociopolitical concerns rather than definitions related to things like mutual intelligibility. In using AAL, we follow Lanehart and Malik (2015:3) in suggesting that calling these speech varieties African American Language varieties, rather than African American English varieties because it is a more neutral term, as it bypasses "some of the problematic implications of 'English' within the socioculture and history of African slave descendants in the United States and the contested connections of their language variety to the motherland and colonization and encompass rhetorical and pragmatic strategies that might not be associated with English." </span></span></li></ul>
<p><span style="font-size:22px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><strong>What is Black American Sign Language?</strong></span></span></p>
<ul><li><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Black American Sign Language is a unique dialect of American Sign Language that developed within historical segregated African American deaf communities throughout the United States. To find out more, you can visit the website for the Language &amp; Life Project's new documentary, <strong><a href="https://www.talkingblackinamerica.org/signing-black-in-america/" target="_blank">Signing Black in America</a></strong>.</span></span></li></ul>
<p><span style="font-size:22px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><strong>Why the <em>Online Resources for African American Language</em> and the <em>Corpus of Regional African American Language</em>?</strong></span></span></p>
<ul><li><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">We saw the need to develop public resources and tools for improving research and education about AAL. Both ORAAL and CORAAL were launched in January 2018. ORAAL seeks to have an engaging, publicly-oriented interface designed to appeal to public users (such as K-12 students and teachers, families, and other non-linguists) in addition to researchers, with supporting contextual and educational information about AAL. There has been an information gap over the last forty years between academics and the general public, such that many of the myths with respect to AAL persist in the public domain to this day. For more about ORAAL, see <strong><a href="/About">About This Project</a></strong>.</span></span></li><li><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">For over 50 years, researchers have turned to spoken language data from African American individuals and communities in order to investigate core, basic questions in sociolinguistics and in the history of American English. Researchers have also studied AAL to combat public myths and prejudice about language. Despite such an intense research tradition, almost no primary data are available for researchers or educators. As social science disciplines, and linguistics in particular, take more seriously issues of replicability, big data, and open-access, it's imperative that publicly available datasets be developed and shared. CORAAL currently includes data from over 150 sociolinguistic interviews and over a million words of time-aligned transcription of conversational speech. For more information, see ORAAL's <strong><a href="/CORAAL">CORAAL</a></strong> page.</span></span></li></ul>
<p><span style="font-size:22px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><strong>References</strong></span></span></p>
<div class="csl-bib-body" style="line-height: 1.35; margin-left: 2em; text-indent:-2em;"><div class="csl-entry"><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Baker-Bell, April. 2020. “Dismantling Anti-Black Linguistic Racism in English Language Arts Classrooms: Toward an Anti-Racist Black Language Pedagogy.” <i>Theory Into Practice</i> 59 (1): 8–21. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/00405841.2019.1665415" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.1080/00405841.2019.1665415</a>.</span></span></div><div class="csl-entry"><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Lanehart, Sonja L., and Ayesha M. Malik. 2015. “Language Use in African American Communities: An Introduction.” In <i>The Oxford Handbook of African American Language</i>, edited by Sonja L. Lanehart, 1–22. Oxford University Press. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199795390.013.62" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199795390.013.62</a>.</span></span></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What is African American Language? African American Language (AAL) varieties are spoken by many African American speakers in the United States.&nbsp;Over the past half century, AAL has been the subject of a great deal of research by linguists and other scholars. Click on any of the links below to learn more about AAL, who speaks it, how it developed, and more!Over several decades, hundreds of researchers have investigated different aspects of AAL. Some prominent early sociolinguists, including William Labov and Walt Wolfram, pioneered the study of the variety. On our Find An Expert page, we celebrate the ongoing contributions of Black scholars researching AAL. Why do you call it "African American Language"? African American Language is a term used to describe language use within the African American community. The speech of African Americans has been called many things by linguists over the years, including Black English, AAVE, AAE, and Ebonics, though these terms may not specifically refer to the same group. Lanehart and Malik (2015:4) suggest that "when speakers know AAL, they know a system of sounds, word and sentence structure, meaning and structural organization of vocabulary items, and other linguistic and metalinguistic information about their language, such as pragmatic rules and the social function of AAL." African American speech is better viewed as a continuum rather than one speech variety. Not every speaker uses all features associated with AAL. For other definitions of AAL, check out What is AAL and who speaks it? Why do scholars and teachers care about AAL? Throughout the half century of sociolinguistic work on AAL varieties, several goals for research have occurred at the same time. For example, William Labov's work in New York City, Walt Wolfram's work in Detroit, and Ralph Fasold's work in Washington DC address core theoretical question to the sociolinguistic enterprise, at the same time, this research was federally funded by the US Office of Education with specific interests in the relationship between vernacular AAL and school performance. Research into reading and AAL, teaching strategies, and acquisition followed. As April Baker-Bell (2020:3) recently wrote in her book, Linguistic Justice: Black Language, Literacy, Identity, and Pedagogy, social justice is linguistic justice: "Linguistic justice is a call to action: a call to radically imagine and create a world free of anti-blackness. A call to create an education system where Black students, their language, their literacies, their culture, their creativity, their joy, their imagination, their brilliance, their freedom, their existence, their resistance MATTERS." What do researchers study about AAL? Researchers study many different aspects of AAL, including linguistic features and how it has changed over time, perceptions and attitudes, the role of AAL in education, language acquisition, regional variation, and bi-dialectalism. For more information, see AAL Linguistic Patterns. To learn about some of the researchers who study different aspects of AAL, please see our Find an Expert page. Where did AAL come from? The origins of AAL have been long debated by linguistic researchers. Several competing positions have emerged, including the Creole Hypothesis, the English Origins Hypothesis, and, most recently, the Substrate Hypothesis. Linguists have used letters written by 18th and 19th century African Americans, written interviews, audio recordings of formerly enslaved individuals, and modern recordings from isolated Black communities to investigate how the speech developed out of the first African Americans and enslaved African peoples in the United States. Most linguists agree that what we now know as AAL primarily developed during the 20th century due to the population movements during the Great Migration and subsequent segregation in large urban centers. For more on the development of AAL, see How did AAL develop? Who speaks AAL? It is difficult to estimate the total number of speakers of a variety, since, as mentioned above, AAL is a continuum. It is true that not all African Americans speak an AAL variety and not all speakers of AAL are African Americans. Some African Americans may speak a variety that aligns more with White Mainstream English, and some non-African Americans may incorporate AAL linguistic features into their speech. Is AAL a language or a dialect? For linguists, the distinction between languages and dialects is often unclear and can be due to sociopolitical concerns rather than definitions related to things like mutual intelligibility. In using AAL, we follow Lanehart and Malik (2015:3) in suggesting that calling these speech varieties African American Language varieties, rather than African American English varieties because it is a more neutral term, as it bypasses "some of the problematic implications of 'English' within the socioculture and history of African slave descendants in the United States and the contested connections of their language variety to the motherland and colonization and encompass rhetorical and pragmatic strategies that might not be associated with English." What is Black American Sign Language? Black American Sign Language is a unique dialect of American Sign Language that developed within historical segregated African American deaf communities throughout the United States. To find out more, you can visit the website for the Language &amp; Life Project's new documentary, Signing Black in America. Why the Online Resources for African American Language and the Corpus of Regional African American Language? We saw the need to develop public resources and tools for improving research and education about AAL. Both ORAAL and CORAAL were launched in January 2018. ORAAL seeks to have an engaging, publicly-oriented interface designed to appeal to public users (such as K-12 students and teachers, families, and other non-linguists) in addition to researchers, with supporting contextual and educational information about AAL. There has been an information gap over the last forty years between academics and the general public, such that many of the myths with respect to AAL persist in the public domain to this day. For more about ORAAL, see About This Project.For over 50 years, researchers have turned to spoken language data from African American individuals and communities in order to investigate core, basic questions in sociolinguistics and in the history of American English. Researchers have also studied AAL to combat public myths and prejudice about language. Despite such an intense research tradition, almost no primary data are available for researchers or educators. As social science disciplines, and linguistics in particular, take more seriously issues of replicability, big data, and open-access, it's imperative that publicly available datasets be developed and shared. CORAAL currently includes data from over 150 sociolinguistic interviews and over a million words of time-aligned transcription of conversational speech. For more information, see ORAAL's CORAAL page. References Baker-Bell, April. 2020. “Dismantling Anti-Black Linguistic Racism in English Language Arts Classrooms: Toward an Anti-Racist Black Language Pedagogy.” Theory Into Practice 59 (1): 8–21. https://doi.org/10.1080/00405841.2019.1665415.Lanehart, Sonja L., and Ayesha M. Malik. 2015. “Language Use in African American Communities: An Introduction.” In The Oxford Handbook of African American Language, edited by Sonja L. Lanehart, 1–22. Oxford University Press. https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199795390.013.62.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">External Data Sources</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/01/external-data-sources.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="External Data Sources" /><published>2020-07-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/01/external-data-sources</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/01/external-data-sources.html"><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><em>External sources</em> includes a wide variety of sources, including sociolinguistic recordings, oral histories, and conversations. Each source listed below includes information about accessing the recordings, recording availability, and external links for further information. If you are looking for downloadable audio with time-aligned transcripts, please see what is available via <a href="https://oraal.uoregon.edu/coraal">CORAAL</a>.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">The following data sources list was prepared by Charlie Farrington and Jaidan McLean. Please contact us at <a href="mailto:OnlineResourcesAAL@gmail.com">OnlineResourcesAAL@gmail.com</a> if you want to suggest more sources to add to this list or you want to include your own data!</span></span></p>
<hr />
<p><a name="AAW Corpus"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">African American Writers 1892-1912 (AAW) Corpus</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">From the Corpus Linguistics in Context (CLiC): "The CLiC Fiction project team (Professor Michaela Mahlberg and Research Fellow Viola Wiegand) have compiled this corpus in collaboration with Nicholas J. Rosato and Claiborne Rice of the University of Louisiana at Lafayette, who had the idea for this corpus and prepared the text files." (<a href="https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/research/activity/corpus/news/2019/aaw-corpus.aspx" target="_blank">Source</a>) This corpus contains novels by Charles W. Chesnutt, Paul Laurence Dunbar, Sutton E. Griggs, Frances E.W. Harper, and James Weldon Johnson.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Information from the University of Birmingham's <a href="https://www.birmingham.ac.uk/research/activity/corpus/news/2019/aaw-corpus.aspx" target="_blank">Centre for Corpus Research</a>, and available through the <a href="https://clic.bham.ac.uk" target="_blank">CLiC web app</a>.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a name="CAL data"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">American English Dialect Recordings: The Center for Applied Linguistics</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">The American English Dialect Recordings collection, available online through the Library of Congress, contains 118 hours of recordings documenting North American English dialects. These include a variety of speech styles, including linguistic interviews, oral histories, conversations, and excerpts from public speeches. They were originally collected as part of Donna Christian's "A Survey and Collection of American English Dialect Recordings" funded by the Center for Applied Linguistics and the National Endowment for the Humanities. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">The following page includes links and demographic information about all of the African American speech samples included in the collection. </span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">For access to the African American speakers available in this collection, please visit Charlie Farrington's <strong><a href="/resources/research/data/cal">American English Dialect Recordings</a></strong> page on ORAAL! Here you will find direct links to Library of Congress pages, which contains both mp3 and wav files.<br /><br />Donna Christian's <em>American English Speech Recordings: A Guide to Collections</em> (Available via <a href="http://eric.ed.gov/?id=ED269965" target="_blank">ERIC</a>) is a directory of collections of audio recordings. This extensive directory gives a state-by-state breakdown of recordings. Published in 1986, this gives background information to the audio available through the CAL digitized collection.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a name="Asheville"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Asheville 1974</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Asheville 1974 is a dataset of sociolinguistic interviews collected by Ronald Butters in Asheville, North Carolina. Forty six recordings were made between May 1974 and August 1974. There are nineteen African American speakers, who are born between 1889 and 1960. Please note that there are young males and older females in the dataset. Located in Western North Carolina's Blue Ridge Mountains, Asheville's population in 1970 was nearly 58,000, and it was home to the Allen School, a notable private school in North Carolina that served black students during segregation in the public school system. These recordings are password protected, but can be accessed through the Sociolinguistic Archive and Analysis Project. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Butters, Ronald. 1981. Unstressed Vowels in Appalachian English. <em>American Speech</em> 56.2: 104-110.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Visit <a href="http://www.language-archives.org/item/oai:ncslaap.lib.ncsu.edu:17" target="_blank">Asheville 1974</a> on OLAC for access information.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a name="Behind the Veil"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Behind the Veil: Documenting African American Life in the Jim Crow South</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Duke University's "The Behind the Veil Oral History Project" was undertaken in 1993 to 1995, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities. From Duke: "The primary purpose of this documentary project was to record and preserve the living memory of African American life during the age of legal segregation in the American South, from the 1890s to the 1950s". "Four hundred and ten of the 1,260 interviews have been digitized and made available on this site totaling about 725 hours of recorded audio. One hundred and sixty five of hte interviews include transcripts comprising more than 15,000 pages of text." The digitized recordings are available freely online, but lossless (e.g., .WAV) recordings can be requested and made available to researchers. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Behind the Veil: Documenting African American Life in the Jim Crow South Digital Collection, John Hope Franklin Research Center, Duke University Libraries.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">This digitized dataset is available through <a href="http://library.duke.edu/digitalcollections/behindtheveil/" target="_blank">Duke University Libraries</a>. For information about the larger collection, visit the <a href="http://library.duke.edu/rubenstein/findingaids/btv/" target="_blank">Collection Guide</a> from the Rubenstein Library at Duke.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a id="DDS" name="DDS"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Detroit Dialect Study</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">The DDS was a foundational study of social stratification in American English in which Roger Shuy and colleagues recorded over 700 white and Black Detroit residents to determine linguistic patterns at play across ethnicity, sex, social class, and age, and the outcomes have informed work on education policy regarding vernacular American English dialects.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">The newly digitized recordings will be available via the Sociolinguistic Archive and Analysis Project (SLAAP).</span></span></p>
<hr />
<p><a id="DARE" name="DARE"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Dictionary of American Regional English</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Between 1965 and 1970, fieldworkers for The Dictionary of American Regional English (DARE) conducted interviews with nearly 3000 informants all across the country. The resulting recordings, which consist of both conversational interviews and the <em>Arthur the Rat </em>reading passage, were digitized, anonymized, and made available through the University of Wisconsin-Madison Libraries Digital Collections. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">The link below includes links and demographic information about all of the African American speech samples included in DARE. </span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">For access to the African American speakers available on DARE, please visit our <strong><a href="/resources/research/data/dare">DARE</a></strong> page on ORAAL! Here you will find direct links to the UW page as well as extensive demographic information.<br /><br />DARE interview files are available in mp3 format from the <a href="http://uwdc.library.wisc.edu/collections/amerlangs/" target="_blank">University of Wisconsin Library</a>. Download CORAAL from CORAAL.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a name="OAARP"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Oregon African American Railroad Porters: Oral History Collection</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">This oral history collection consists of 20 primary speakers across 30 recordings, two of which are from a Senior Citizens Association Meeting and include multiple unknown speakers. While the African American population in Oregon is quite small, the economic impact the community has had on Oregon has been substantial through the railroad system. These recordings were conducted in the 1980’s, with a brief description of the interview's topics provided. Audio files and transcripts are available through the Oregon State University Collections and Archives Research Center.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Oregon State University. 2016. <em>African American Railroad Porters Oral History Collection (OH 29)</em>. Corvallis, OR: Oregon State University Special Collections and Archives Research Center.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Available through the <a href="http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu/oh29/interviews.html" target="_blank">Oregon State University Libraries</a>.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a name="Roanoke"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Roanoke Island</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Roanoke Island, North Carolina recordings were made in 2003 by members of the Language and Life Project. There are 35 African American speakers in the SLAAP Roanoke Island project, including twenty males and fifteen females, born between 1921 and 1991. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">From The Language and Life Project: "Roanoke Island, a thirteen-mile island in the Croatan and Roanoke Sounds, located between the Outer Banks and the mainland coast of North Carolina, is well known as the site of the Lost Colony, where the first settlement of British colonists disappeared in 1587. The untold story of Roanoke Island, however, is its role in the development of Outer Banks African American speech. During the Civil War, the 1862 Battle of Roanoke Island ended Confederate resistance along the Outer Banks and stripped the Confederate army of one of their most vibrant maritime routes for provisions. This Union victory also escalated an influx of freed and runaway slaves to the North Carolina coast and compelled the creation of the Freedmen's Colony of Roanoke Island. The goal of this Freedmen's Colony was to establish a self-sufficient African American community. By the end of the Civil War, the population of the Freedmen's Colony of Roanoke Island was nearly 3500. Unfortunately, the colony was disbanded when the former residents of the island demanded their land back after the war. Following the forced disintegration of the Freedmen's colony, about 300 African American residents remained on Roanoke Island. Many of the approximately 250 current African American residents of Roanoke Island can trace their ancestry back to these people who remained on the island from the Freedmen's Colony."</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Carpenter, Jeannine. 2004. The lost community of the Outer Banks: African American speech on Roanoke Island. Master's thesis. Raleigh: North Carolina State University. </span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Visit <a href="http://www.language-archives.org/item/oai:ncslaap.lib.ncsu.edu:5" target="_blank">Roanoke Island</a> on OLAC for access information.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a name="Robeson"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Robeson County</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">The Language and Life Project conducted interviews with over a hundred Robeson County, North Carolina speakers. There are 23 recordings of African American speakers in the SLAAP archive, including six males and seventeen females. Robeson County is a tri-ethnic community located on Interstate 95 near the South Carolina border. Native Americans comprise approximately 40 percent of the county population, African Americans 25 percent, and Anglo Americans the remaining 35 percent.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">From The Language and Life Project: "According to historical records, early Anglo settlers from the Scottish Highlands, some of whom were Gaelic speakers, found the Lumbee, the Native-American group within the county, speaking English when they arrived in the Robeson County area in the 1730s. A group of African Americans, including both runaway and free slaves, was also scattered in the region at the time, so that the three ethnic groups have lived in this region for almost three centuries. The ethnic relations of the three groups have shifted through time in response to various sociopolitical events, including the desegregation of county school in the early 1970s. Despite some increase in intercommunication among the three ethnicities, ethnic boundaries remain strong; and Robeson County in large part continues to exist in a state of de facto segregation into three ethnic communities."</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Wolfram, Walt, and Clare J. Dannenberg. 1999. Dialect identity in a triethnic context: The case of Lumbee American Indian English. <em>English World-Wide</em>, 20.: 79-116.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Visit <a href="http://www.language-archives.org/item/oai:ncslaap.lib.ncsu.edu:20" target="_blank">Robeson County</a> on OLAC for access information.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a id="Rochester Voices" name="Rochester Voices"><span style="font-size:22px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Rochester Voices</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Rochester Voices is the home of the Phillis Wheatley Public Library Oral History Collection. These oral history recordings, done between 1978 and 1981, highlight the public contributions of African Americans in the Rochester area focusing on occupations, attitudes and roles in the community, discussing things like housing discrimination, segregation, and employment barriers. These recordings nicely completement CORAAL's Rochester component of recordings made by Dr. Sharese King in 2016! </span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">For information about the speakers in the Rochester Voices collection, visit our <strong><a href="/resources/research/data/rochester-voices">Rochester Voices</a></strong> page on ORAAL. Here you will find direct links to the audio pages as well as demographic information.<br /><br />Recordings are available to stream at <a href="http://www.rochestervoices.org/collections/african-american-oral-histories/" target="_blank">www.rochestervoices.org</a>, and WAV files of recordings are available upon request.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a id="ExSlave Recordings" name="ExSlave Recordings"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Voices Remembering Slavery: Freed People Tell Their Stories</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">This collection consists of 23 primary speakers across 63 recordings. The age of the speakers range from 1842 to 1882, with the majority being over 80 years old. These recordings were taken between the years 1932 and 1975, and across 9 states.The individuals discuss their life of enslavement and life after freedom, and some sing songs that they learned as slaves. Unfortunately, not all of the recordings are clearly audible due to background noise and microphone issues. Some time-aligned transcripts of these recordings are available through the Sociolinguistic Archive and Analysis Project. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Bailey, Guy, Natalie Maynor, and Patricia Cukor-Avila (eds.). 1991. <em>The Emergence of Black English: Text and Commentary</em>. Amsterdam/Philadelphia: John Benjamins. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1075/cll.8" itemprop="sameAs" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.1075/cll.8</a></span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">For more information about speakers, recordings, and teaching resources, please visit <a href="http://www.loc.gov/collections/voices-remembering-slavery/about-this-collection" target="_blank">Voices Remembering Slavery</a> on the <a href="http://www.loc.gov/" target="_blank">Library of Congress</a>. For information on TextGrids available on SLAAP, please contact us.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p><a name="Wilmington"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Wilmington 1973</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Wilmington 1973 consists of 79 individual interviews across 79 recordings. This collection was collected by Ronald Butters in Wilmington, North Carolina between July 1973 and August 1974, and includes speakers born between 1893 and 1957. There are 31 African American participants, including 20 males and 11 females. Located on the southern North Carolina coast, sitting along the Cape Fear River, Wilmington's 1970 population was just over 46,000, and was 34.3% African American. These recordings can be accessed through the Sociolinguistic Archive and Analysis Project. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Butters, Ronald R. and Ruth A. Nix. 1986. <em>The English of Blacks in Wilmington, NC. </em>In Michael B. Montgomery and Guy Bailey (eds.), <em>Language Variety in the South: Perspectives in Black and White</em>. Tuscaloosa: University of Alabama Press, 254-263.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Thomas, Erik R. 1989. The implications of /o/ fronting in Wilmington, North Carolina. <em>American Speech 64</em>: 327-333.</span></span></p>
<div style="background:#eeeeee;border:1px solid #cccccc;padding:5px 10px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Visit <a href="http://www.language-archives.org/item/oai:ncslaap.lib.ncsu.edu:29" target="_blank">Wilmington 1973</a> on OLAC for access information.</span></span></div>
<hr />
<p style="text-align: right;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><a href="#top">Back to top of page</a></span></p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Charlie Farrington, March 2023 (last update)</span></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[External sources includes a wide variety of sources, including sociolinguistic recordings, oral histories, and conversations. Each source listed below includes information about accessing the recordings, recording availability, and external links for further information. If you are looking for downloadable audio with time-aligned transcripts, please see what is available via CORAAL. The following data sources list was prepared by Charlie Farrington and Jaidan McLean. Please contact us at OnlineResourcesAAL@gmail.com if you want to suggest more sources to add to this list or you want to include your own data! African American Writers 1892-1912 (AAW) Corpus From the Corpus Linguistics in Context (CLiC): "The CLiC Fiction project team (Professor Michaela Mahlberg and Research Fellow Viola Wiegand) have compiled this corpus in collaboration with Nicholas J. Rosato and Claiborne Rice of the University of Louisiana at Lafayette, who had the idea for this corpus and prepared the text files." (Source) This corpus contains novels by Charles W. Chesnutt, Paul Laurence Dunbar, Sutton E. Griggs, Frances E.W. Harper, and James Weldon Johnson. Information from the University of Birmingham's Centre for Corpus Research, and available through the CLiC web app. American English Dialect Recordings: The Center for Applied Linguistics The American English Dialect Recordings collection, available online through the Library of Congress, contains 118 hours of recordings documenting North American English dialects. These include a variety of speech styles, including linguistic interviews, oral histories, conversations, and excerpts from public speeches. They were originally collected as part of Donna Christian's "A Survey and Collection of American English Dialect Recordings" funded by the Center for Applied Linguistics and the National Endowment for the Humanities. The following page includes links and demographic information about all of the African American speech samples included in the collection. For access to the African American speakers available in this collection, please visit Charlie Farrington's American English Dialect Recordings page on ORAAL! Here you will find direct links to Library of Congress pages, which contains both mp3 and wav files.Donna Christian's American English Speech Recordings: A Guide to Collections (Available via ERIC) is a directory of collections of audio recordings. This extensive directory gives a state-by-state breakdown of recordings. Published in 1986, this gives background information to the audio available through the CAL digitized collection. Asheville 1974 Asheville 1974 is a dataset of sociolinguistic interviews collected by Ronald Butters in Asheville, North Carolina. Forty six recordings were made between May 1974 and August 1974. There are nineteen African American speakers, who are born between 1889 and 1960. Please note that there are young males and older females in the dataset. Located in Western North Carolina's Blue Ridge Mountains, Asheville's population in 1970 was nearly 58,000, and it was home to the Allen School, a notable private school in North Carolina that served black students during segregation in the public school system. These recordings are password protected, but can be accessed through the Sociolinguistic Archive and Analysis Project. Butters, Ronald. 1981. Unstressed Vowels in Appalachian English. American Speech 56.2: 104-110. Visit Asheville 1974 on OLAC for access information. Behind the Veil: Documenting African American Life in the Jim Crow South Duke University's "The Behind the Veil Oral History Project" was undertaken in 1993 to 1995, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities. From Duke: "The primary purpose of this documentary project was to record and preserve the living memory of African American life during the age of legal segregation in the American South, from the 1890s to the 1950s". "Four hundred and ten of the 1,260 interviews have been digitized and made available on this site totaling about 725 hours of recorded audio. One hundred and sixty five of hte interviews include transcripts comprising more than 15,000 pages of text." The digitized recordings are available freely online, but lossless (e.g., .WAV) recordings can be requested and made available to researchers. Behind the Veil: Documenting African American Life in the Jim Crow South Digital Collection, John Hope Franklin Research Center, Duke University Libraries. This digitized dataset is available through Duke University Libraries. For information about the larger collection, visit the Collection Guide from the Rubenstein Library at Duke. Detroit Dialect Study The DDS was a foundational study of social stratification in American English in which Roger Shuy and colleagues recorded over 700 white and Black Detroit residents to determine linguistic patterns at play across ethnicity, sex, social class, and age, and the outcomes have informed work on education policy regarding vernacular American English dialects. The newly digitized recordings will be available via the Sociolinguistic Archive and Analysis Project (SLAAP). Dictionary of American Regional English Between 1965 and 1970, fieldworkers for The Dictionary of American Regional English (DARE) conducted interviews with nearly 3000 informants all across the country. The resulting recordings, which consist of both conversational interviews and the Arthur the Rat reading passage, were digitized, anonymized, and made available through the University of Wisconsin-Madison Libraries Digital Collections. The link below includes links and demographic information about all of the African American speech samples included in DARE. For access to the African American speakers available on DARE, please visit our DARE page on ORAAL! Here you will find direct links to the UW page as well as extensive demographic information.DARE interview files are available in mp3 format from the University of Wisconsin Library. Download CORAAL from CORAAL. Oregon African American Railroad Porters: Oral History Collection This oral history collection consists of 20 primary speakers across 30 recordings, two of which are from a Senior Citizens Association Meeting and include multiple unknown speakers. While the African American population in Oregon is quite small, the economic impact the community has had on Oregon has been substantial through the railroad system. These recordings were conducted in the 1980’s, with a brief description of the interview's topics provided. Audio files and transcripts are available through the Oregon State University Collections and Archives Research Center. Oregon State University. 2016. African American Railroad Porters Oral History Collection (OH 29). Corvallis, OR: Oregon State University Special Collections and Archives Research Center. Available through the Oregon State University Libraries. Roanoke Island Roanoke Island, North Carolina recordings were made in 2003 by members of the Language and Life Project. There are 35 African American speakers in the SLAAP Roanoke Island project, including twenty males and fifteen females, born between 1921 and 1991. From The Language and Life Project: "Roanoke Island, a thirteen-mile island in the Croatan and Roanoke Sounds, located between the Outer Banks and the mainland coast of North Carolina, is well known as the site of the Lost Colony, where the first settlement of British colonists disappeared in 1587. The untold story of Roanoke Island, however, is its role in the development of Outer Banks African American speech. During the Civil War, the 1862 Battle of Roanoke Island ended Confederate resistance along the Outer Banks and stripped the Confederate army of one of their most vibrant maritime routes for provisions. This Union victory also escalated an influx of freed and runaway slaves to the North Carolina coast and compelled the creation of the Freedmen's Colony of Roanoke Island. The goal of this Freedmen's Colony was to establish a self-sufficient African American community. By the end of the Civil War, the population of the Freedmen's Colony of Roanoke Island was nearly 3500. Unfortunately, the colony was disbanded when the former residents of the island demanded their land back after the war. Following the forced disintegration of the Freedmen's colony, about 300 African American residents remained on Roanoke Island. Many of the approximately 250 current African American residents of Roanoke Island can trace their ancestry back to these people who remained on the island from the Freedmen's Colony." Carpenter, Jeannine. 2004. The lost community of the Outer Banks: African American speech on Roanoke Island. Master's thesis. Raleigh: North Carolina State University. Visit Roanoke Island on OLAC for access information. Robeson County The Language and Life Project conducted interviews with over a hundred Robeson County, North Carolina speakers. There are 23 recordings of African American speakers in the SLAAP archive, including six males and seventeen females. Robeson County is a tri-ethnic community located on Interstate 95 near the South Carolina border. Native Americans comprise approximately 40 percent of the county population, African Americans 25 percent, and Anglo Americans the remaining 35 percent. From The Language and Life Project: "According to historical records, early Anglo settlers from the Scottish Highlands, some of whom were Gaelic speakers, found the Lumbee, the Native-American group within the county, speaking English when they arrived in the Robeson County area in the 1730s. A group of African Americans, including both runaway and free slaves, was also scattered in the region at the time, so that the three ethnic groups have lived in this region for almost three centuries. The ethnic relations of the three groups have shifted through time in response to various sociopolitical events, including the desegregation of county school in the early 1970s. Despite some increase in intercommunication among the three ethnicities, ethnic boundaries remain strong; and Robeson County in large part continues to exist in a state of de facto segregation into three ethnic communities." Wolfram, Walt, and Clare J. Dannenberg. 1999. Dialect identity in a triethnic context: The case of Lumbee American Indian English. English World-Wide, 20.: 79-116. Visit Robeson County on OLAC for access information. Rochester Voices Rochester Voices is the home of the Phillis Wheatley Public Library Oral History Collection. These oral history recordings, done between 1978 and 1981, highlight the public contributions of African Americans in the Rochester area focusing on occupations, attitudes and roles in the community, discussing things like housing discrimination, segregation, and employment barriers. These recordings nicely completement CORAAL's Rochester component of recordings made by Dr. Sharese King in 2016! For information about the speakers in the Rochester Voices collection, visit our Rochester Voices page on ORAAL. Here you will find direct links to the audio pages as well as demographic information.Recordings are available to stream at www.rochestervoices.org, and WAV files of recordings are available upon request. Voices Remembering Slavery: Freed People Tell Their Stories This collection consists of 23 primary speakers across 63 recordings. The age of the speakers range from 1842 to 1882, with the majority being over 80 years old. These recordings were taken between the years 1932 and 1975, and across 9 states.The individuals discuss their life of enslavement and life after freedom, and some sing songs that they learned as slaves. Unfortunately, not all of the recordings are clearly audible due to background noise and microphone issues. Some time-aligned transcripts of these recordings are available through the Sociolinguistic Archive and Analysis Project. Bailey, Guy, Natalie Maynor, and Patricia Cukor-Avila (eds.). 1991. The Emergence of Black English: Text and Commentary. Amsterdam/Philadelphia: John Benjamins. https://doi.org/10.1075/cll.8 For more information about speakers, recordings, and teaching resources, please visit Voices Remembering Slavery on the Library of Congress. For information on TextGrids available on SLAAP, please contact us. Wilmington 1973 Wilmington 1973 consists of 79 individual interviews across 79 recordings. This collection was collected by Ronald Butters in Wilmington, North Carolina between July 1973 and August 1974, and includes speakers born between 1893 and 1957. There are 31 African American participants, including 20 males and 11 females. Located on the southern North Carolina coast, sitting along the Cape Fear River, Wilmington's 1970 population was just over 46,000, and was 34.3% African American. These recordings can be accessed through the Sociolinguistic Archive and Analysis Project. Butters, Ronald R. and Ruth A. Nix. 1986. The English of Blacks in Wilmington, NC. In Michael B. Montgomery and Guy Bailey (eds.), Language Variety in the South: Perspectives in Black and White. Tuscaloosa: University of Alabama Press, 254-263. Thomas, Erik R. 1989. The implications of /o/ fronting in Wilmington, North Carolina. American Speech 64: 327-333. Visit Wilmington 1973 on OLAC for access information. Back to top of page Charlie Farrington, March 2023 (last update)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bibliography of African American Language Research</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/30/bibliography-of-african-american-language-research.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bibliography of African American Language Research" /><published>2020-06-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/30/bibliography-of-african-american-language-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/30/bibliography-of-african-american-language-research.html"><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">The Bibliography of African American Language Research was created by Charlie Farrington with additional help by Chloe Tacata. Charlie Farrington maintains the bibliography. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">How to cite this bibliography:</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Farrington, Charlie. 2023. Bibliography of African American Language Research. </span></span><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">This bibliography was created in <strong><a href="https://www.zotero.org/" target="_blank">Zotero</a></strong> and the contents of this page were automatically generated using <a href="https://bibbase.org/" target="_blank"><strong>BibBase</strong></a>. The title links take you to a separate BibBase page where you can add to your library or add a comment. These pages are not monitored by the ORAAL team.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">Please allow time for reference list to load.</span></span></p>
<script src="https://bibbase.org/show?bib=https%3A%2F%2Fbibbase.org%2Fzotero%2FCorpusAAL&amp;jsonp=1"></script>
<p style="text-align: right;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><a href="#top">Back to top of page</a></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:22px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Additional Bibliographic References</span></span></p>
<div class="csl-bib-body" style="line-height: 1.35; margin-left: 2em; text-indent:-2em;"><div class="csl-entry"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Brasch, Ila Wales, and Walter M. Brasch. 1974. <i>A Comprehensive Annotated Bibliography of American Black English</i>. Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press.</span></span></div><div class="csl-entry"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">McMillan, James B., and Michael Montgomery. 1989. <i>Annotated Bibliography of Southern American English</i>. Tuscaloosa: University of Alabama Press.</span></span></div><div class="csl-entry"><span style="font-size:16px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Rickford, John R., Julie Sweetland, Angela E. Rickford, and Thomas Grano. 2013. <i>African American, Creole and Other Vernacular Englishes in Education: A Bibliographic Resource</i>. NCTE-Routledge Research Series 4. New York: Routledge,Taylor &amp; Francis ; National Council of Teachers of English.</span></span></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Bibliography of African American Language Research was created by Charlie Farrington with additional help by Chloe Tacata. Charlie Farrington maintains the bibliography. How to cite this bibliography: Farrington, Charlie. 2023. Bibliography of African American Language Research. Eugene, OR: The Online Resources for African American Language Project. This bibliography was created in Zotero and the contents of this page were automatically generated using BibBase. The title links take you to a separate BibBase page where you can add to your library or add a comment. These pages are not monitored by the ORAAL team. Please allow time for reference list to load. Back to top of page Additional Bibliographic References Brasch, Ila Wales, and Walter M. Brasch. 1974. A Comprehensive Annotated Bibliography of American Black English. Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press.McMillan, James B., and Michael Montgomery. 1989. Annotated Bibliography of Southern American English. Tuscaloosa: University of Alabama Press.Rickford, John R., Julie Sweetland, Angela E. Rickford, and Thomas Grano. 2013. African American, Creole and Other Vernacular Englishes in Education: A Bibliographic Resource. NCTE-Routledge Research Series 4. New York: Routledge,Taylor &amp; Francis ; National Council of Teachers of English.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Linguists who work on AAL</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/28/linguists-who-work-on-aal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Linguists who work on AAL" /><published>2020-06-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/28/linguists-who-work-on-aal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/28/linguists-who-work-on-aal.html"><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">On this page, we highlight Black linguists who have contributed to the study of African American Language in the United States. Some have worked on AAL in the variationist sociolinguistic paradigm, while others focus on educational or psycholinguistic questions. This list is not meant to be exhaustive. At the bottom of the page, we include an <strong><a href="#In Memoriam">In Memoriam</a></strong> section.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">If you have a suggestion for an addition, or if you are on this list and want to be removed, please contact us at <a href="mailto:OnlineResourcesAAL@gmail.com?subject=ORAAL%20Black%20Linguists%20List%20Addition%20Request">OnlineResourcesAAL@gmail.com</a>.</span></span></p>
<div class="listing listing--photo-right"><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>H. Samy Alim</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>David O. Sears Presidential Endowed Chair and Professor of Anthropology and African American Studies, University of California, Los Angeles</p><p><a href="https://anthro.ucla.edu/faculty/h-samy-alim" target="_blank">https://anthro.ucla.edu/faculty/h-samy-alim</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>April Baker-Bell</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor of Language, Literacy, and English Education, Department of English, Michigan State University</p><p><a href="https://english.msu.edu/faculty/april-baker-bell/" target="_blank">https://english.msu.edu/faculty/april-baker-bell/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Arnetha Ball</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Charles E. Ducommun Endowed Professor (Emerita), Graduate School of Education, Stanford University</p><p><a href="http://web.stanford.edu/dept/gse/cgi-bin/arnetha/?" target="_blank">http://web.stanford.edu/dept/gse/cgi-bin/arnetha/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>John Baugh</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Margaret Bush Wilson Professor in Arts &amp; Sciences, Washington University in St. Louis</p><p><a href="https://psych.wustl.edu/people/john-baugh" target="_blank">https://psych.wustl.edu/people/john-baugh</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Renée Blake</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor of Linguistics and Social &amp; Cultural Analysis, New York University</p><p><a href="https://as.nyu.edu/faculty/renee-blake.html" target="_blank">https://as.nyu.edu/faculty/renee-blake.html</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Jennifer Bloomquist</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Provost for Faculty Development, Dean of Social Sciences and Interdisciplinary Programs, Professor, Gettysburg College</p><p><a href="https://www.gettysburg.edu/academic-programs/africana-studies/faculty/employee_detail.dot?empId=82174024320013261" target="_blank">Faculty Page</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Dominique Branson</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Ph.D. Student, Department of Linguistics, University of Pittsburgh</p><p><a href="https://dominiquebranson.com/" target="_blank">https://dominiquebranson.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Erica Britt</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor, University of Michigan Flint</p><p><a href="https://umflint.academia.edu/EricaBritt" target="_blank">https://umflint.academia.edu/EricaBritt</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Kendra Calhoun</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>UC President's Postdoctoral Fellow, Department of Anthropology, UCLA</p><p><a href="https://kendrancalhoun.com/" target="_blank">https://kendrancalhoun.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Dominique Canning</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Ph.D. Candidate, Department of Linguistics, University of Michigan</p><p><a href="https://lsa.umich.edu/linguistics/people/graduate-students/dominique-canning.html" target="_blank">https://lsa.umich.edu/linguistics/people/graduate-students/dominique-canning.html</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Anne Charity Hudley</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor of Education, Stanford University</p><p><a href="https://annecharityhudley.com/" target="_blank">https://annecharityhudley.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Tracy Conner</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Assistant Professor, School of Communication, Northwestern University</p><p><a href="https://tracyconner.academia.edu/" target="_blank">https://tracyconner.academia.edu/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Charles DeBose</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor Emeritus, Department of English, Cal State East Bay</p><p><a href="https://www.csueastbay.edu/directory/profiles/engl/debosecharles.html" target="_blank">https://www.csueastbay.edu/directory/profiles/engl/debosecharles.html</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Michel DeGraff</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor of Linguistics, Department of Linguistics and Philosophy, Massachusetts Institute of Technology</p><p><a href="https://linguistics.mit.edu/user/degraff/" target="_blank">https://linguistics.mit.edu/user/degraff/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Walter F. Edwards</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor of Linguistics, Director of Humanities Center, Wayne State University</p><p><a href="https://research2.wayne.edu/hum/AboutUs/ourstaff.html" target="_blank">https://research2.wayne.edu/hum/AboutUs/ourstaff.html</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Sabriya Fisher</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Diana Chapman Walsh Assistant Professor of Cognitive and Linguistic Sciences, Wellesley College</p><p><a href="https://www.sabriya-fisher.com/" target="_blank">https://www.sabriya-fisher.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Shivonne Gates</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Impact Lead, Frontline</p><p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/smgates/" target="_blank">https://sites.google.com/view/smgates/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Akiemi Glenn</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Executive Director, The Pōpolo Project</p><p><a href="https://akiemiglenn.net" target="_blank">https://akiemiglenn.net</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Shelome Gooden</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor, Department of Linguistics, University of Pittsburgh</p><p><a href="https://www.linguistics.pitt.edu/people/shelome-gooden" target="_blank">https://www.linguistics.pitt.edu/people/shelome-gooden</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Lisa Green</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor, Department of Linguistics, University of Massachusetts Amherst</p><p><a href="https://people.umass.edu/lisag/" target="_blank">https://people.umass.edu/lisag/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Jessi Grieser</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor, Department of Linguistics, University of Michigan</p><p><a href="https://jessgrieser.com/" target="_blank">https://jessgrieser.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Shenika Hankerson</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Assistant Professor, Department of Teaching and Learning, Policy and Leadership, University of Maryland</p><p><a href="https://education.umd.edu/directory/shenika-hankerson" target="_blank">https://education.umd.edu/directory/shenika-hankerson</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Joseph Hill</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor, Department of ASL and Interpreting Education, Rochester Institute of Technology</p><p><a href="https://www.josephchill.com/" target="_blank">https://www.josephchill.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Nicole Holliday</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Assistant Professor, Department of Linguistics and Cognitive Science, Pomona College</p><p><a href="https://nicolerholliday.wordpress.com/" target="_blank">https://nicolerholliday.wordpress.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Yolanda Holt</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor, Department of Communication Sciences &amp; Disorders, East Carolina University</p><p><a href="http://blog.ecu.edu/sites/ppsholt/" target="_blank">http://blog.ecu.edu/sites/ppsholt/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Tiffany M. Jones</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Assistant Professor of Anthropology, William Rainey Harper College</p><p><a href="https://tiffanymarquisejones.com/" target="_blank">https://tiffanymarquisejones.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Sharese King</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Neubauer Family Assistant Professor, Department of Linguistics, The University of Chicago</p><p><a href="https://www.drshareseking.com/" target="_blank">https://www.drshareseking.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Sonja Lanehart</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor of Linguistics, College of Social and Behavioral Sciences, University of Arizona</p><p><a href="https://www.sonjallanehart.com/" target="_blank">https://www.sonjallanehart.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Qiuana Lopez</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Assistant Project Specialist, University of California, Santa Barbara</p><p><a href="https://independent.academia.edu/QiuanaLopez" target="_blank">https://independent.academia.edu/QiuanaLopez</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Zion Mengesha</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Ph.D. Candidate, Department of Linguistics, Stanford University</p><p><a href="https://www.zionmengesha.com/" target="_blank">https://www.zionmengesha.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>John H. McWhorter</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor, Slavic Department, Columbia University</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Carolyn McCaskill</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor, Department of ASL and Deaf Studies, Gallaudet University</p><p><a href="http://blackaslproject.gallaudet.edu/Bios/Carolyn_McCaskill.html" target="_blank">http://blackaslproject.gallaudet.edu/Bios/Carolyn_McCaskill.html</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>deandre a. miles-hercules</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Ph.D. Student, Department of Linguistics, University of California, Santa Barbara</p><p><a href="https://www.linguistics.ucsb.edu/people/deandre-miles-hercules">https://www.linguistics.ucsb.edu/people/deandre-miles-hercules</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>David Mitchell</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Assistant Professor, Department of English, Metropolitan State University of Denver</p><p><a href="https://webapp.msudenver.edu/directory/profile.php?uName=dmitch58" target="_blank">https://webapp.msudenver.edu/directory/profile.php?uName=dmitch58</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Claudia Mitchell-Kernan</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor Emerita, Department of African American Studies, Princeton University</p><p><a href="https://aas.princeton.edu/people/claudia-mitchell-kernan" target="_blank">https://aas.princeton.edu/people/claudia-mitchell-kernan</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Simanique Moody</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Assistant Professor, Department of English, Brooklyn College</p><p><a href="http://www.brooklyn.cuny.edu/web/academics/schools/socialsciences/departments/english/faculty_details.php?faculty=1418" target="_blank">http://www.brooklyn.cuny.edu/web/academics/schools/socialsciences/departments/english/faculty_details.php?faculty=1418</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Marcyliena Morgan</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Ernest E. Monrad Professor of the Social Sciences, Professor of African and African American Studies, Executive Director of the HipHop Archive and Research Institute, Harvard University</p><p><a href="https://aaas.fas.harvard.edu/people/marcyliena-morgan" target="_blank">https://aaas.fas.harvard.edu/people/marcyliena-morgan</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Salikoko Mufwene</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Frank J. McLoraine Distinguished Service Professor, Department of Linguistics, University of Chicago</p><p><a href="http://mufwene.uchicago.edu/" target="_blank">http://mufwene.uchicago.edu/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Jamaal Muwwakkil</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Ph.D. Candidate, Department of Linguistics, University of California, Santa Barbara</p><p><a href="https://www.wordsbyjamaal.com/" target="_blank">https://www.wordsbyjamaal.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Monica Nesbitt</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Assistant Professor, Department of Linguistics, Indiana University</p><p><a href="https://monnesbitt.github.io/Website/" target="_blank">https://monnesbitt.github.io/Website/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Brandi Newkirk-Turner</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor and Chair, Department of Communicative Disorders, Jacksonville State University</p><p><a href="https://www.jsums.edu/commdisorders/cd-faculty/newkirk-turner-2/" target="_blank">https://www.jsums.edu/commdisorders/cd-faculty/newkirk-turner-2/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Django Paris</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>James A. &amp; Cherry A. Banks Professor of Multicultural Education, College of Education, University of Washington</p><p><a href="https://education.uw.edu/people/dparis" target="_blank">https://education.uw.edu/people/dparis</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Staci Perryman-Clark</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor of English, Department of English, Western Michigan University</p><p><a href="https://wmich.edu/english/directory/perryman-clark">https://wmich.edu/english/directory/perryman-clark</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Sarah Phillips</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Postdoctoral Scholar, Georgetown University Medical Center</p><p><a href="https://sarahfphillips.com/" target="_blank">https://sarahfphillips.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Jaylen Pittman</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Ph.D. Student, Department of Linguistics, University of California, Santa Barbara</p><p><a href="https://www.linguistics.ucsb.edu/people/jaylen-pittman" target="_blank">https://www.linguistics.ucsb.edu/people/jaylen-pittman</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Mackenzie Price</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Director, Anti-Bias Initiatives, Dotdash Meredith</p><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mackenzie-price-phd-15b61065/" target="_blank">https://www.linkedin.com/in/mackenzie-price-phd-15b61065/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Minnie Quartey</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Senior Director, Strategic Initiatives, Boys &amp; Girls Clubs of Greater Washington DC</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Jacquelyn Rahman</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor of Linguistics, Department of English, Miami University</p><p><a href="https://miamioh.edu/cas/academics/departments/english/about/faculty_staff/faculty-alphabetical/rahman-jacquelyn/index.html" target="_blank">https://miamioh.edu/cas/academics/departments/english/about/faculty_staff/faculty-alphabetical/rahman-jacquelyn/index.html</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Elaine Richardson</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor, Department of Teaching and Learning, The Ohio State University</p><p><a href="https://u.osu.edu/richardson.486/" target="_blank">https://u.osu.edu/richardson.486/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Angela E. Rickford</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor, Special Education, San Jose State University</p><p><a href="https://www.sjsu.edu/people/angela.rickford/" target="_blank">https://www.sjsu.edu/people/angela.rickford/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>John Rickford</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>J.E. Wallace Sterling Professor of the Humanities, Department of Linguistics, Emeritus, Stanford University</p><p><a href="http://johnrickford.com/" target="_blank">http://johnrickford.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Harry Seymour</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor Emeritus, Department of Communication Disorders, University of Massachusetts</p><p><a href="https://www.umass.edu/aae/hseymour.htm">https://www.umass.edu/aae/hseymour.htm</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Nandi Sims</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Assistant Professor, Stanford University</p><p><a href="https://nandisims.github.io/" target="_blank">https://nandisims.github.io/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Walter Sistrunk</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Assistant Professor, Education and Language Acquisition Department, LaGuardia Community College</p><p><a href="http://cuny.is/wsistrunk" target="_blank">http://cuny.is/wsistrunk</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Hiram Smith</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor of Spanish, Bucknell University</p><p><a href="https://www.bucknell.edu/fac-staff/hiram-smith">https://www.bucknell.edu/fac-staff/hiram-smith</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Geneva Smitherman</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>University Distinguished Professor Emerita, Department of English, Michigan State University</p><p><a href="https://msu.edu/~smither4/">https://msu.edu/~smither4/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Arthur K. Spears</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor of Linguistics and Anthropology, The City University of New York</p><p><a href="http://arthurkspears.com/wordpress/" target="_blank">http://arthurkspears.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Ida Stockman</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Emeritus Faculty, Department of Communicative Sciences &amp; Disorders, Michigan State University</p><p><a href="https://comartsci.msu.edu/our-people/ida-stockman">https://comartsci.msu.edu/our-people/ida-stockman</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Orlando Taylor</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Distinguished Senior Advisor to the President, Fielding Graduate University</p><p><a href="https://expertfile.com/experts/orlando.taylorphd" target="_blank">https://expertfile.com/experts/orlando.taylorphd</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>J. Michael Terry</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor, Department of Linguistics, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</p><p><a href="https://unc.academia.edu/JMichaelTerry" target="_blank">https://unc.academia.edu/JMichaelTerry</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Nicole Patton Terry</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Olive &amp; Manuel Bordas Professor of Education, School of Teacher Education, Florida State University</p><p><a href="https://fcrr.org/person/nicole-patton-terry-phd" target="_blank">https://fcrr.org/person/nicole-patton-terry-phd</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Jamie A. Thomas</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Assistant Professor of Linguistics, Santa Monica College</p><p><a href="https://www.jamieathomas.com/" target="_blank">https://www.jamieathomas.com/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Denise Troutman</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor, Department of Writing, Rhetoric, and American Cultures, Department of Linguistics and Languages, Michigan State University</p><p><a href="http://linglang.msu.edu/people/faculty/denise-troutman/" target="_blank">http://linglang.msu.edu/people/faculty/denise-troutman/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Julie A. Washington</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor, School of Education, University of California, Irvine</p><p><a href="https://education.uci.edu/washington_bio.html" target="_blank">https://education.uci.edu/washington_bio.html</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Alicia Beckford Wassink</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor, Department of Linguistics, University of Washington</p><p><a href="https://depts.washington.edu/sociolab/Wassink/Wassink.php/" target="_blank">https://depts.washington.edu/sociolab/Wassink/Wassink.php/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Rachel Elizabeth Weissler</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Postdoctoral Fellow, Department of Linguistics, University of Oregon</p><p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/rachel-elizabeth-weissler">https://sites.google.com/view/rachel-elizabeth-weissler</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Tracey Weldon</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Vice President of Executive Search, Greenwood Asher &amp; Associates</p><p><a href="https://greenwoodsearch.com/team-members/tracey-weldon/" target="_blank">https://greenwoodsearch.com/team-members/tracey-weldon/</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Bonnie J. Williams-Farrier</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor, Department of English, Comparative Literature, and Linguistics, California State University, Fullerton</p><p><a href="http://english.fullerton.edu/faculty/profile/b_williams.aspx" target="_blank">http://english.fullerton.edu/faculty/profile/b_williams.aspx</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Kelly Elizabeth Wright</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Postdoctoral Research Fellow, Department of English, Virginia Tech University</p><p><a href="https://kellywright5.wixsite.com/raciolinguistics" target="_blank">https://kellywright5.wixsite.com/raciolinguistics</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Mary Zeigler</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Associate Professor of English Language and Linguistics, English Department, Georgia State University</p><p><a href="https://english.gsu.edu/emeritus-faculty/mary-e-brown-zeigler/" target="_blank">https://english.gsu.edu/emeritus-faculty/mary-e-brown-zeigler/</a></p></div></div></div><p>&nbsp;</p><p style="text-align: right;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><a href="#top">Back to top of page</a></span></p><div class="section-header section-header--green"><div class="section-header__title"><p><a id="In Memoriam" name="In Memoriam"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:24px;">In memoriam</span></span></a></p></div></div><div class="listing listing--photo-right"><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>William Edward Farrison (1902 - 1985)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Dr. Farrison completed his Ph.D. in linguistics at the Ohio State Univerity in 1936, with his dissertation, <em>The phonology of the illiterate Negro dialect of Guilford County, North Carolina</em>, available <a href="https://etd.ohiolink.edu/!etd.send_file?accession=osu1392218527&amp;disposition=inline" target="_blank">here</a>. He taught at Lincoln University in Pennsylvania (1926-1928), West Virginia State (1928-1931), Bennett College (1932-1939), and North Carolina Central University (1939-1970), where he retired. He published numerous articles on the English language, speech, and literature of African Americans, including the definitive biography of William Wells Brown.</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Jerrie C. Scott (1944 - 2017)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Dr. Scott completed her Ph.D. in linguistics at the University of Michigan. She authored numerous books and articles, and founded the <a href="https://ncte.org/get-involved/african-american-read-in/" target="_blank">National African American Read-In</a>. See&nbsp;<a href="https://ncte.org/blog/2019/01/sawobuna-see-jerrie-continuing-legacy-african-american-read/" target="_blank"><em>Sawubona (“I see you”), Jerrie: Continuing the Legacy of the African American Read-In</em></a> on the National Council of Teachers of English blog, written by Dr. Stephanie Power-Carter and Dr. David E. Kirkland.</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Gary Simpkins (1943 - 2009)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Dr. Simpkins completed his Ed.D. at the University of Massachusetts in 1976. He was one of the creators of the BRIDGE program, and published about language, reading and education among African American children. See <a href="https://blacklanguagematters.com/in-memoriam/dr-gary-simpkins/" target="_blank">Word: The Online Journal on African American English</a>'s page dedicated to Dr. Simpkins.</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Lorenzo Dow Turner (1890 - 1972)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Dr. Turner completed his Ph.D. in linguistics at the University of Chicago. Check out the Linguistic Society of America's <a href="https://www.linguisticsociety.org/content/month-linguistics-history-tribute-lorenzo-dow-turner" target="_blank">Tribute to Lorenzo Dow Turner</a>. Also check out Dr. Margaret Wade-Lewis's (2007) biography, <a href="https://www.sc.edu/uscpress/books/2007/3628.html" target="_blank"><em>Lorenzo Dow Turner, Father of Gullah Studies</em></a>. Recenlty, the Amistad Research Center in New Orleans digitized some of Dr. Turner's Field Recordings with help from the Council on Library and Information Resources. More information is available <a href="https://soundcloud.com/user-754569376/sets/turner-recordings/s-IarPR" target="_blank">here</a>, and you can stream the audio via <a href="https://soundcloud.com/user-754569376/sets/turner-recordings/s-IarPR" target="_blank">Soundcloud</a>.</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Fay Vaughn-Cooke (1947 - 2010)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Professor, University of Maryland Eastern Shore. Dr. Vaughn-Cooke received her Ph.D. from Georgetown University in 1976, with her dissertation, <em>The Implementation of a Phonological Change: The Case of Resyllabification in Black English</em>. She went on to work on speech language pathology and language acquisition in the speech of African American children in Washington DC.</p><p><a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C38&amp;q=anna+fay+vaughn+cooke&amp;btnG=" target="_blank">Google Scholar</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Margaret Wade-Lewis (1945 - 2009)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Dr. Wade-Lewis was a historian of African American linguists, and served as the Department Chair and Associate Professor of Linguistics and Literature in the Department of Black Studies at the State University of New York at New Paltz. She was the first African American woman to receive her Ph.D. in linguistics from NYU (1988).</p><p><a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;as_sdt=0%2C38&amp;q=margaret+wade-lewis&amp;btnG=" target="_blank">Google Scholar</a></p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Mark Hanna Watkins (1903 - 1976)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Dr. Watkins was a University of Chicago trained linguist whose dissertation was a descriptive grammar of Chichewa (a Bantu language). In 2018, Dr. Arthur K. Spears&nbsp; wrote about Dr. Watkins for the Linguistics Society of America for Black History Month. You can find that article <a href="https://www.linguisticsociety.org/content/month-linguistics-history-tribute-mark-hanna-watkins" target="_blank">here</a>. While Dr. Watkins did not work on the speech of African Americans, we want to celebrate his contributions to linguistics as the first African American to receive his PhD in linguistics in the United States.</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Darnell Williams (1944 - 2021)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Dr. Williams was the former Dean of Social Sciences and Education at Langston University in Langston, Oklahoma. His 1973 dissertation, An investigation of possible Gullah survivals in the speech and cultural patterns of Black Mississippians, focused on the social and linguistic lives of Black Mississippians. He was also active in assisting smaller African American colleges in preparing for accreditation</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Robert Lee Williams II (1930 - 2020)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Dr. Williams was Professor Emeritus of Psychology and African and Afro-American studies at Washington University in St. Louis. A prolific psychologist, Dr. Williams is perhaps best known in linguistic circles for coining the term <em>Ebonics</em> to refer to the speech of African Americans in 1973. In 2018, Patricia Griffin interviewed Dr. Williams for the Arkansas Association of Black Psychologists Oral History Project, the audio is available on the <strong><a href="https://cdm15728.contentdm.oclc.org/digital/collection/p1532coll1/id/16637/rec/1" target="_blank">Central Arkansas Library System</a></strong>.</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Juanita Williamson (1917 - 1993)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Dr. Williamson was a Professor of English and Chair of the Humanities at LeMoyne-Owen College in Memphis, Tennessee. She was well known in the fields of linguistics, education, and reading, but readers here might be most familiar with her dissertation and subsequent 1968 monograph for the Publication of the American Dialect Society, <a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/pads/issue/50/1" target="_blank">A Phonological and Morphological Study of the Speech of the Negro of Memphis, Tennessee</a>. For more information about Dr. Williamson, see her <a href="http://womenofachievement.org/heritage/juanita-williamson/" target="_blank">Women of Achievement</a> write up.</p></div></div></div></div></div>
<p style="text-align: right;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><a href="#top">Back to top of page</a></span></p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><span style="font-family:Times New Roman,Times,serif;">Charlie Farrington, March 2023</span></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On this page, we highlight Black linguists who have contributed to the study of African American Language in the United States. Some have worked on AAL in the variationist sociolinguistic paradigm, while others focus on educational or psycholinguistic questions. This list is not meant to be exhaustive. At the bottom of the page, we include an In Memoriam section. If you have a suggestion for an addition, or if you are on this list and want to be removed, please contact us at OnlineResourcesAAL@gmail.com. H. Samy AlimDavid O. Sears Presidential Endowed Chair and Professor of Anthropology and African American Studies, University of California, Los Angeleshttps://anthro.ucla.edu/faculty/h-samy-alimApril Baker-BellAssociate Professor of Language, Literacy, and English Education, Department of English, Michigan State Universityhttps://english.msu.edu/faculty/april-baker-bell/Arnetha BallCharles E. Ducommun Endowed Professor (Emerita), Graduate School of Education, Stanford Universityhttp://web.stanford.edu/dept/gse/cgi-bin/arnetha/John BaughMargaret Bush Wilson Professor in Arts &amp; Sciences, Washington University in St. Louishttps://psych.wustl.edu/people/john-baughRenée BlakeAssociate Professor of Linguistics and Social &amp; Cultural Analysis, New York Universityhttps://as.nyu.edu/faculty/renee-blake.htmlJennifer BloomquistAssociate Provost for Faculty Development, Dean of Social Sciences and Interdisciplinary Programs, Professor, Gettysburg CollegeFaculty PageDominique BransonPh.D. Student, Department of Linguistics, University of Pittsburghhttps://dominiquebranson.com/Erica BrittAssociate Professor, University of Michigan Flinthttps://umflint.academia.edu/EricaBrittKendra CalhounUC President's Postdoctoral Fellow, Department of Anthropology, UCLAhttps://kendrancalhoun.com/Dominique CanningPh.D. Candidate, Department of Linguistics, University of Michiganhttps://lsa.umich.edu/linguistics/people/graduate-students/dominique-canning.htmlAnne Charity HudleyProfessor of Education, Stanford Universityhttps://annecharityhudley.com/Tracy ConnerAssistant Professor, School of Communication, Northwestern Universityhttps://tracyconner.academia.edu/Charles DeBoseProfessor Emeritus, Department of English, Cal State East Bayhttps://www.csueastbay.edu/directory/profiles/engl/debosecharles.htmlMichel DeGraffProfessor of Linguistics, Department of Linguistics and Philosophy, Massachusetts Institute of Technologyhttps://linguistics.mit.edu/user/degraff/Walter F. EdwardsProfessor of Linguistics, Director of Humanities Center, Wayne State Universityhttps://research2.wayne.edu/hum/AboutUs/ourstaff.htmlSabriya FisherDiana Chapman Walsh Assistant Professor of Cognitive and Linguistic Sciences, Wellesley Collegehttps://www.sabriya-fisher.com/Shivonne GatesImpact Lead, Frontlinehttps://sites.google.com/view/smgates/Akiemi GlennExecutive Director, The Pōpolo Projecthttps://akiemiglenn.netShelome GoodenProfessor, Department of Linguistics, University of Pittsburghhttps://www.linguistics.pitt.edu/people/shelome-goodenLisa GreenProfessor, Department of Linguistics, University of Massachusetts Amhersthttps://people.umass.edu/lisag/Jessi GrieserAssociate Professor, Department of Linguistics, University of Michiganhttps://jessgrieser.com/Shenika HankersonAssistant Professor, Department of Teaching and Learning, Policy and Leadership, University of Marylandhttps://education.umd.edu/directory/shenika-hankersonJoseph HillAssociate Professor, Department of ASL and Interpreting Education, Rochester Institute of Technologyhttps://www.josephchill.com/Nicole HollidayAssistant Professor, Department of Linguistics and Cognitive Science, Pomona Collegehttps://nicolerholliday.wordpress.com/Yolanda HoltAssociate Professor, Department of Communication Sciences &amp; Disorders, East Carolina Universityhttp://blog.ecu.edu/sites/ppsholt/Tiffany M. JonesAssistant Professor of Anthropology, William Rainey Harper Collegehttps://tiffanymarquisejones.com/Sharese KingNeubauer Family Assistant Professor, Department of Linguistics, The University of Chicagohttps://www.drshareseking.com/Sonja LanehartProfessor of Linguistics, College of Social and Behavioral Sciences, University of Arizonahttps://www.sonjallanehart.com/Qiuana LopezAssistant Project Specialist, University of California, Santa Barbarahttps://independent.academia.edu/QiuanaLopezZion MengeshaPh.D. Candidate, Department of Linguistics, Stanford Universityhttps://www.zionmengesha.com/John H. McWhorterAssociate Professor, Slavic Department, Columbia UniversityCarolyn McCaskillProfessor, Department of ASL and Deaf Studies, Gallaudet Universityhttp://blackaslproject.gallaudet.edu/Bios/Carolyn_McCaskill.htmldeandre a. miles-herculesPh.D. Student, Department of Linguistics, University of California, Santa Barbarahttps://www.linguistics.ucsb.edu/people/deandre-miles-herculesDavid MitchellAssistant Professor, Department of English, Metropolitan State University of Denverhttps://webapp.msudenver.edu/directory/profile.php?uName=dmitch58Claudia Mitchell-KernanProfessor Emerita, Department of African American Studies, Princeton Universityhttps://aas.princeton.edu/people/claudia-mitchell-kernanSimanique MoodyAssistant Professor, Department of English, Brooklyn Collegehttp://www.brooklyn.cuny.edu/web/academics/schools/socialsciences/departments/english/faculty_details.php?faculty=1418Marcyliena MorganErnest E. Monrad Professor of the Social Sciences, Professor of African and African American Studies, Executive Director of the HipHop Archive and Research Institute, Harvard Universityhttps://aaas.fas.harvard.edu/people/marcyliena-morganSalikoko MufweneFrank J. McLoraine Distinguished Service Professor, Department of Linguistics, University of Chicagohttp://mufwene.uchicago.edu/Jamaal MuwwakkilPh.D. Candidate, Department of Linguistics, University of California, Santa Barbarahttps://www.wordsbyjamaal.com/Monica NesbittAssistant Professor, Department of Linguistics, Indiana Universityhttps://monnesbitt.github.io/Website/Brandi Newkirk-TurnerAssociate Professor and Chair, Department of Communicative Disorders, Jacksonville State Universityhttps://www.jsums.edu/commdisorders/cd-faculty/newkirk-turner-2/Django ParisJames A. &amp; Cherry A. Banks Professor of Multicultural Education, College of Education, University of Washingtonhttps://education.uw.edu/people/dparisStaci Perryman-ClarkAssociate Professor of English, Department of English, Western Michigan Universityhttps://wmich.edu/english/directory/perryman-clarkSarah PhillipsPostdoctoral Scholar, Georgetown University Medical Centerhttps://sarahfphillips.com/Jaylen PittmanPh.D. Student, Department of Linguistics, University of California, Santa Barbarahttps://www.linguistics.ucsb.edu/people/jaylen-pittmanMackenzie PriceDirector, Anti-Bias Initiatives, Dotdash Meredithhttps://www.linkedin.com/in/mackenzie-price-phd-15b61065/Minnie QuarteySenior Director, Strategic Initiatives, Boys &amp; Girls Clubs of Greater Washington DCJacquelyn RahmanAssociate Professor of Linguistics, Department of English, Miami Universityhttps://miamioh.edu/cas/academics/departments/english/about/faculty_staff/faculty-alphabetical/rahman-jacquelyn/index.htmlElaine RichardsonProfessor, Department of Teaching and Learning, The Ohio State Universityhttps://u.osu.edu/richardson.486/Angela E. RickfordProfessor, Special Education, San Jose State Universityhttps://www.sjsu.edu/people/angela.rickford/John RickfordJ.E. Wallace Sterling Professor of the Humanities, Department of Linguistics, Emeritus, Stanford Universityhttp://johnrickford.com/Harry SeymourProfessor Emeritus, Department of Communication Disorders, University of Massachusettshttps://www.umass.edu/aae/hseymour.htmNandi SimsAssistant Professor, Stanford Universityhttps://nandisims.github.io/Walter SistrunkAssistant Professor, Education and Language Acquisition Department, LaGuardia Community Collegehttp://cuny.is/wsistrunkHiram SmithAssociate Professor of Spanish, Bucknell Universityhttps://www.bucknell.edu/fac-staff/hiram-smithGeneva SmithermanUniversity Distinguished Professor Emerita, Department of English, Michigan State Universityhttps://msu.edu/~smither4/Arthur K. SpearsProfessor of Linguistics and Anthropology, The City University of New Yorkhttp://arthurkspears.com/Ida StockmanEmeritus Faculty, Department of Communicative Sciences &amp; Disorders, Michigan State Universityhttps://comartsci.msu.edu/our-people/ida-stockmanOrlando TaylorDistinguished Senior Advisor to the President, Fielding Graduate Universityhttps://expertfile.com/experts/orlando.taylorphdJ. Michael TerryAssociate Professor, Department of Linguistics, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hillhttps://unc.academia.edu/JMichaelTerryNicole Patton TerryOlive &amp; Manuel Bordas Professor of Education, School of Teacher Education, Florida State Universityhttps://fcrr.org/person/nicole-patton-terry-phdJamie A. ThomasAssistant Professor of Linguistics, Santa Monica Collegehttps://www.jamieathomas.com/Denise TroutmanAssociate Professor, Department of Writing, Rhetoric, and American Cultures, Department of Linguistics and Languages, Michigan State Universityhttp://linglang.msu.edu/people/faculty/denise-troutman/Julie A. WashingtonProfessor, School of Education, University of California, Irvinehttps://education.uci.edu/washington_bio.htmlAlicia Beckford WassinkProfessor, Department of Linguistics, University of Washingtonhttps://depts.washington.edu/sociolab/Wassink/Wassink.php/Rachel Elizabeth WeisslerPostdoctoral Fellow, Department of Linguistics, University of Oregonhttps://sites.google.com/view/rachel-elizabeth-weisslerTracey WeldonVice President of Executive Search, Greenwood Asher &amp; Associateshttps://greenwoodsearch.com/team-members/tracey-weldon/Bonnie J. Williams-FarrierAssociate Professor, Department of English, Comparative Literature, and Linguistics, California State University, Fullertonhttp://english.fullerton.edu/faculty/profile/b_williams.aspxKelly Elizabeth WrightPostdoctoral Research Fellow, Department of English, Virginia Tech Universityhttps://kellywright5.wixsite.com/raciolinguisticsMary ZeiglerAssociate Professor of English Language and Linguistics, English Department, Georgia State Universityhttps://english.gsu.edu/emeritus-faculty/mary-e-brown-zeigler/&nbsp;Back to top of pageIn memoriamWilliam Edward Farrison (1902 - 1985)Dr. Farrison completed his Ph.D. in linguistics at the Ohio State Univerity in 1936, with his dissertation, The phonology of the illiterate Negro dialect of Guilford County, North Carolina, available here. He taught at Lincoln University in Pennsylvania (1926-1928), West Virginia State (1928-1931), Bennett College (1932-1939), and North Carolina Central University (1939-1970), where he retired. He published numerous articles on the English language, speech, and literature of African Americans, including the definitive biography of William Wells Brown.Jerrie C. Scott (1944 - 2017)Dr. Scott completed her Ph.D. in linguistics at the University of Michigan. She authored numerous books and articles, and founded the National African American Read-In. See&nbsp;Sawubona (“I see you”), Jerrie: Continuing the Legacy of the African American Read-In on the National Council of Teachers of English blog, written by Dr. Stephanie Power-Carter and Dr. David E. Kirkland.Gary Simpkins (1943 - 2009)Dr. Simpkins completed his Ed.D. at the University of Massachusetts in 1976. He was one of the creators of the BRIDGE program, and published about language, reading and education among African American children. See Word: The Online Journal on African American English's page dedicated to Dr. Simpkins.Lorenzo Dow Turner (1890 - 1972)Dr. Turner completed his Ph.D. in linguistics at the University of Chicago. Check out the Linguistic Society of America's Tribute to Lorenzo Dow Turner. Also check out Dr. Margaret Wade-Lewis's (2007) biography, Lorenzo Dow Turner, Father of Gullah Studies. Recenlty, the Amistad Research Center in New Orleans digitized some of Dr. Turner's Field Recordings with help from the Council on Library and Information Resources. More information is available here, and you can stream the audio via Soundcloud.Fay Vaughn-Cooke (1947 - 2010)Professor, University of Maryland Eastern Shore. Dr. Vaughn-Cooke received her Ph.D. from Georgetown University in 1976, with her dissertation, The Implementation of a Phonological Change: The Case of Resyllabification in Black English. She went on to work on speech language pathology and language acquisition in the speech of African American children in Washington DC.Google ScholarMargaret Wade-Lewis (1945 - 2009)Dr. Wade-Lewis was a historian of African American linguists, and served as the Department Chair and Associate Professor of Linguistics and Literature in the Department of Black Studies at the State University of New York at New Paltz. She was the first African American woman to receive her Ph.D. in linguistics from NYU (1988).Google ScholarMark Hanna Watkins (1903 - 1976)Dr. Watkins was a University of Chicago trained linguist whose dissertation was a descriptive grammar of Chichewa (a Bantu language). In 2018, Dr. Arthur K. Spears&nbsp; wrote about Dr. Watkins for the Linguistics Society of America for Black History Month. You can find that article here. While Dr. Watkins did not work on the speech of African Americans, we want to celebrate his contributions to linguistics as the first African American to receive his PhD in linguistics in the United States.Darnell Williams (1944 - 2021)Dr. Williams was the former Dean of Social Sciences and Education at Langston University in Langston, Oklahoma. His 1973 dissertation, An investigation of possible Gullah survivals in the speech and cultural patterns of Black Mississippians, focused on the social and linguistic lives of Black Mississippians. He was also active in assisting smaller African American colleges in preparing for accreditationRobert Lee Williams II (1930 - 2020)Dr. Williams was Professor Emeritus of Psychology and African and Afro-American studies at Washington University in St. Louis. A prolific psychologist, Dr. Williams is perhaps best known in linguistic circles for coining the term Ebonics to refer to the speech of African Americans in 1973. In 2018, Patricia Griffin interviewed Dr. Williams for the Arkansas Association of Black Psychologists Oral History Project, the audio is available on the Central Arkansas Library System.Juanita Williamson (1917 - 1993)Dr. Williamson was a Professor of English and Chair of the Humanities at LeMoyne-Owen College in Memphis, Tennessee. She was well known in the fields of linguistics, education, and reading, but readers here might be most familiar with her dissertation and subsequent 1968 monograph for the Publication of the American Dialect Society, A Phonological and Morphological Study of the Speech of the Negro of Memphis, Tennessee. For more information about Dr. Williamson, see her Women of Achievement write up. Back to top of page Charlie Farrington, March 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Resources for Post-Secondary Educators</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/27/resources-for-post-secondary-educators.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Resources for Post-Secondary Educators" /><published>2020-06-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/27/resources-for-post-secondary-educators</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/27/resources-for-post-secondary-educators.html"><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">While much of the work on AAL for educators is geared towards primary and secondary education, on this page we focus on materials for the study of AAL and other non-mainstream varieties in the college classroom. Like our <a href="/resources/educational/K-12">Resources for K-12 Educators</a> page, we include links to videos, other websites, and books that might be off interest. To learn more about AAL more generally, visit <a href="/resources/educational/learn-more">Learn More about AAL</a> and our <a href="/AAL">AAL Facts</a> page!</span></span></p>
<hr />
<p><a id="Videos" name="Videos"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Videos</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Documentaries (Full Length)</span></span></p>
<div class="listing listing--photo-left"><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__photo"><p>&nbsp;</p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/l-AR5hCQcd4" target="_blank"><span>[[{"fid":"102","view_mode":"default","fields":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""},"type":"media","field_deltas":{"3":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""}},"link_text":null,"attributes":{"height":169,"width":300,"class":"media-element file-default","data-delta":"3"}}]]</span></a></p></div><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Talking Black in America (2017)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>"The creativity and resilience of people living through oppression, segregation and the fight for equality, and the powerful identity forged by a shared heritage are all expressed in the ways African Americans communicate. TALKING BLACK in AMERICA chronicles the incredible impact of African American English on American language and culture. Filmed across the United States, this documentary is a revelation of language as legacy, identity and triumph over adversity." (from <a href="https://languageandlife.org" target="_blank">The Language and Life Project</a>)</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__photo"><p>&nbsp;</p><p><a href="https://youtu.be/B4mONY5AMG4" target="_blank"><span>[[{"fid":"103","view_mode":"default","fields":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""},"type":"media","field_deltas":{"4":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""}},"link_text":null,"attributes":{"height":169,"width":300,"class":"media-element file-default","data-delta":"4"}}]]</span></a></p></div><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Signing Black in America (2020)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>"Black ASL is the unique dialect of American Sign Language (ASL) that developed within historically segregated African American Deaf communities. Largely unknown to outsiders, Black ASL has become a symbol of solidarity and a vital part of identity within the Black Deaf community. Different uses of space, hand use, directional movement, and facial expression are some of the ways it sets itself apart from other varieties of ASL. With the perspectives of Black signers, Sign Language interpreters, and the scholars who have worked to uncover it, SIGNING BLACK in AMERICA explores the history and development of this unique and expressive variety of visual communication." (from <a href="https://languageandlife.org" target="_blank">The Language and Life Project</a>)</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__photo"><p>&nbsp;</p><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dAGG3LnEVvI" target="_blank"><span>[[{"fid":"104","view_mode":"default","fields":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""},"type":"media","field_deltas":{"5":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""}},"link_text":null,"attributes":{"height":164,"width":300,"class":"media-element file-default","data-delta":"5"}}]]</span></a></p></div><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Voices of North Carolina (2005)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>"One State, Many Voices – From the furthest reaches of the Outer Banks to the heights of the Southern Appalachian Highlands, an incredible diversity of people call North Carolina home. Cherokee and Lumbee Indians, African Americans, and first language Spanish-speakers all contribute their voices in this rich portrait of language and identity." (from <a href="https://languageandlife.org" target="_blank">The Language and Life Project</a>). The clip, African Americans in North Carolina, is available as a standalone clip <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RTt07IVDeww" target="_blank">here</a>.</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__photo"><p>&nbsp;</p><p>[[{"fid":"100","view_mode":"default","fields":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":"DYSA title card","field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"DYSA title card","title":""},"type":"media","field_deltas":{"1":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":"DYSA title card","field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"DYSA title card","title":""}},"link_text":null,"attributes":{"alt":"DYSA title card","height":171,"width":300,"class":"media-element file-default","data-delta":"1"}}]]</p></div><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>Do You Speak American? (2005)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>Do You Speak American? was a three-part PBS miniseries that explored language use in the United States. Host Robert MacNeil investigates the question, "what does it mean to speak American?" The three parts can regularly be found streaming on YouTube, though no official streams are available. High School and College curricula were developed by sociolinguists to support the miniseries and are available on the <a href="http://www.pbs.org/speak/education/" target="_blank">Do You Speak American website</a>.</p></div></div></div><div class="listing__row"><div class="listing__photo"><p>&nbsp;</p><p>[[{"fid":"101","view_mode":"default","fields":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""},"type":"media","field_deltas":{"2":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""}},"link_text":null,"attributes":{"height":169,"width":300,"class":"media-element file-default","data-delta":"2"}}]]</p></div><div class="listing__content"><div class="listing__title"><p>American Tongues (1988)</p></div><div class="listing__teaser"><p>American Tongues is a 1988 sociolinguistic documentary that examines American English dialects and perceptions. While the documentary is over 30 years old, it is still regularly used in colleges, universities and other training settings. It is available to stream on <a href="https://www.kanopy.com/" target="_blank">Kanopy</a>,</p></div></div></div></div>
<p><span style="font-size:18px;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;">For more clips and excerpts, visit our <a href="/resources/educational/learn-more">Learn More</a> page!</span></span></p>
<hr />
<p><a id="Links" name="Links"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Web Links</span></span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Curricula and Materials for AAL</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;"><a href="https://www.pbs.org/speak/education/" target="_blank">Do You Speak American? For Educators</a> - <em>Do You Speak American?</em> was a 2005 documentary series produced by PBS. On their companion website, there is plenty of information for educators, focused mainly on high school and college levels (available <a href="https://www.pbs.org/speak/education/" target="_blank">here</a>), including specific curricula for the study of African American English in the classroom.</span></span></p>
<ul><li><a href="https://www.pbs.org/speak/education/curriculum/college/aae/" target="_blank"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">African American English Curriculum (College)</span></span></a></li></ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:22px;">Language Diversity on Campus</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">At North Carolina State University, the <a href="https://howl.wordpress.ncsu.edu/" target="_blank">Language Diversity Ambassadors</a>, a graduate student run outreach group, promotes awareness about linguistic diversity and linguistic discrimination on NC State's campus as well as society at large. They are in the process making several resources available on their website. Research by Stephany Dunston and colleagues (<em>The Importance of Graduate Student Engagement in a Campus Language Diversity Initiative, Journal of English Linguistics, Vol. 46(3):215-228) </em>suggests that student involvement in such initiatives is critical to reach diverse audiences, both on campus and in the community, but this engagement also teaches them the importance of engagement and being able to communicate research to a wider audience.</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size:20px;"><span style="font-family:Trebuchet MS,Helvetica,sans-serif;">Sociolinguistic Artifacts</span></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size:18px;">The <a href="https://www.reed.edu/slx-artifacts/" target="_blank">Sociolinguistic Artifacts</a> website was developed by Kara Becker at Reed College as a way to collect and curate sociolinguistically relevant media content. The website is frequently updated with contributions by students and other users. Each artifact submission comes with a description of the content and several tags to make searching easier. The screenshot below is the front page for artifacts tagged with African American Language (also available <a href="https://www.reed.edu/slx-artifacts/tags/Linguistic%20Variety/African%20American%20Language.php" target="_blank">here</a>)</span></span></p>
<p><span><img alt="Screenshot from Sociolinguistic Artifacts website" class="media-element file-default" data-delta="3" data-fid="79" data-media-element="1" src="https://oraal-stage.uoregon.edu/sites/oraal2.uoregon.edu/files/Screen%20Shot%202019-11-06%20at%201.04.39%20PM.png" style="height: 424px; width: 500px;" typeof="foaf:Image" width="1025" height="870" /></span></p>
<hr />
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ul></ul>
<p style="text-align: right;"><span style="font-family:Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif;"><a href="#top">Back to top of page</a></span></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[While much of the work on AAL for educators is geared towards primary and secondary education, on this page we focus on materials for the study of AAL and other non-mainstream varieties in the college classroom. Like our Resources for K-12 Educators page, we include links to videos, other websites, and books that might be off interest. To learn more about AAL more generally, visit Learn More about AAL and our AAL Facts page! Videos Documentaries (Full Length) &nbsp;[[{"fid":"102","view_mode":"default","fields":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""},"type":"media","field_deltas":{"3":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""}},"link_text":null,"attributes":{"height":169,"width":300,"class":"media-element file-default","data-delta":"3"}}]]Talking Black in America (2017)"The creativity and resilience of people living through oppression, segregation and the fight for equality, and the powerful identity forged by a shared heritage are all expressed in the ways African Americans communicate. TALKING BLACK in AMERICA chronicles the incredible impact of African American English on American language and culture. Filmed across the United States, this documentary is a revelation of language as legacy, identity and triumph over adversity." (from The Language and Life Project)&nbsp;[[{"fid":"103","view_mode":"default","fields":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""},"type":"media","field_deltas":{"4":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""}},"link_text":null,"attributes":{"height":169,"width":300,"class":"media-element file-default","data-delta":"4"}}]]Signing Black in America (2020)"Black ASL is the unique dialect of American Sign Language (ASL) that developed within historically segregated African American Deaf communities. Largely unknown to outsiders, Black ASL has become a symbol of solidarity and a vital part of identity within the Black Deaf community. Different uses of space, hand use, directional movement, and facial expression are some of the ways it sets itself apart from other varieties of ASL. With the perspectives of Black signers, Sign Language interpreters, and the scholars who have worked to uncover it, SIGNING BLACK in AMERICA explores the history and development of this unique and expressive variety of visual communication." (from The Language and Life Project)&nbsp;[[{"fid":"104","view_mode":"default","fields":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""},"type":"media","field_deltas":{"5":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""}},"link_text":null,"attributes":{"height":164,"width":300,"class":"media-element file-default","data-delta":"5"}}]]Voices of North Carolina (2005)"One State, Many Voices – From the furthest reaches of the Outer Banks to the heights of the Southern Appalachian Highlands, an incredible diversity of people call North Carolina home. Cherokee and Lumbee Indians, African Americans, and first language Spanish-speakers all contribute their voices in this rich portrait of language and identity." (from The Language and Life Project). The clip, African Americans in North Carolina, is available as a standalone clip here.&nbsp;[[{"fid":"100","view_mode":"default","fields":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":"DYSA title card","field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"DYSA title card","title":""},"type":"media","field_deltas":{"1":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":"DYSA title card","field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"DYSA title card","title":""}},"link_text":null,"attributes":{"alt":"DYSA title card","height":171,"width":300,"class":"media-element file-default","data-delta":"1"}}]]Do You Speak American? (2005)Do You Speak American? was a three-part PBS miniseries that explored language use in the United States. Host Robert MacNeil investigates the question, "what does it mean to speak American?" The three parts can regularly be found streaming on YouTube, though no official streams are available. High School and College curricula were developed by sociolinguists to support the miniseries and are available on the Do You Speak American website.&nbsp;[[{"fid":"101","view_mode":"default","fields":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""},"type":"media","field_deltas":{"2":{"format":"default","alignment":"","field_file_image_alt_text[und][0][value]":false,"field_file_image_title_text[und][0][value]":false,"alt":"","title":""}},"link_text":null,"attributes":{"height":169,"width":300,"class":"media-element file-default","data-delta":"2"}}]]American Tongues (1988)American Tongues is a 1988 sociolinguistic documentary that examines American English dialects and perceptions. While the documentary is over 30 years old, it is still regularly used in colleges, universities and other training settings. It is available to stream on Kanopy, For more clips and excerpts, visit our Learn More page! Web Links Curricula and Materials for AAL Do You Speak American? For Educators - Do You Speak American? was a 2005 documentary series produced by PBS. On their companion website, there is plenty of information for educators, focused mainly on high school and college levels (available here), including specific curricula for the study of African American English in the classroom. African American English Curriculum (College) &nbsp; Language Diversity on Campus At North Carolina State University, the Language Diversity Ambassadors, a graduate student run outreach group, promotes awareness about linguistic diversity and linguistic discrimination on NC State's campus as well as society at large. They are in the process making several resources available on their website. Research by Stephany Dunston and colleagues (The Importance of Graduate Student Engagement in a Campus Language Diversity Initiative, Journal of English Linguistics, Vol. 46(3):215-228) suggests that student involvement in such initiatives is critical to reach diverse audiences, both on campus and in the community, but this engagement also teaches them the importance of engagement and being able to communicate research to a wider audience. Sociolinguistic Artifacts The Sociolinguistic Artifacts website was developed by Kara Becker at Reed College as a way to collect and curate sociolinguistically relevant media content. The website is frequently updated with contributions by students and other users. Each artifact submission comes with a description of the content and several tags to make searching easier. The screenshot below is the front page for artifacts tagged with African American Language (also available here) &nbsp; Back to top of page]]></summary></entry></feed>